<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Dutch drawn to life</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 169 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 84 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37094</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">8119167</idno>
  <idno type="VID">40895</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264206970</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2898</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24309</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">08119167</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.  Navigations series.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37094)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40895)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1228:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Dutch drawn to life</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>156 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Johnson, and H. Marsh,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"In I. an exact description and character of the several provinces of the Netherlands, II. an account of their trade and industry, III. a well-weigh'd re-search into their policy, government, and strength, IV. a particular discourse of their religion and customes, V. a close narrative of the way and method whereby they made themselves a free state under the conduct of the Prince of Aurange : whereunto is added the lives of the 5 last Princes, VI. a continued history of the last war, together with their dealings with England, from the year 1612 to the year 1660."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Netherlands --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Netherlands --  Politics and government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40895:1"/>
            <p>THE DUTCH Drawn to the LIFE, IN</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. An Exact Description and Character of the several Provinces of the <hi>Netherlands.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. An Account of their Trade and Industry.</item>
               <item>III. A well-weigh'd re-search into their Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, Government, and Strength.</item>
               <item>IV. A particular Discourse of their Religion and Customes.</item>
               <item>V. A close Narrative of the way and Method whereby they made themselves a Free State, under the conduct of the Prince of <hi>Aurange:</hi> Whereunto is added the Lives of the 5. last Princes.</item>
               <item>VI. A continued History of the last War, together with their Dealings wit<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> from the year 1612. to the year 1660.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Johnson,</hi> at the Key in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Churchyard, and <hi>H. Marsh,</hi> at the Princes Arms in <hi>Chancery lane,</hi> 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:40895:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40895:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Piece is not the Melancholy Conceit, the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle Transport, or the narrow and short Observations of any Single, or Impertinent Person, but an Exact Collection of what the most Sage States-men, the most Reserved Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians,
<pb facs="tcp:40895:3"/> the most Judicious Historians, the most Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Travellers, the most Critical and Deep Discoursers have bequeath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us, concerning this great Scene of Wit and Industry, Prudence and Business, Skill and Activity, Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience and Success: Here are the Profound Courtier <hi>Bentivoglio</hi>'s Exact Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters and Descriptions; the Apprehensive &amp; Quick Favorite, <hi>Overbury,</hi> his Weighty Reflexions; the Rational and Publick spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited Writer, Sir <hi>John
<pb facs="tcp:40895:3"/> Burroughs,</hi> his Ʋsefull Discoveries; the Ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Travellers, Mr. <hi>How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Feltham's</hi> smart Resentments; the Grave Writer, Mr <hi>Shute</hi>'s Methodical History; Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite <hi>Strada</hi>'s Prudent Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moires; Active <hi>Stroud,</hi> and <hi>Scot</hi>'s solid Conclusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;—In a word, the Low-Countries give you a short Map and View of what the whole World sheweth you at Large; and this Book is the Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tessence of what whole Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes have been taken up
<pb facs="tcp:40895:4"/> with; What would you know in the Ʋniverse, that you shall not see in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?</hi> and what would you understand of <hi>Holland,</hi> that you see not here? both are <hi>all</hi> in a Little; the Book and the Argument; both <hi>Europe</hi> in <hi>Amster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam Print.—</hi> Would the <hi>Speculativi</hi> see whether a Monarchy or a Common-wealth? Here the Question is Decided. Would the Tradesman Thrive? here is the best Exchange. Would the Souldier or Mariner Excell in their way? here
<pb facs="tcp:40895:4"/> is Skill and Experience; Would the Libertine enjoy his Conscience? here is that Mystery revealed; Would you compare their Strength with ours? here it is done to your hands; Is Trade dead? here is the reason of it; Are we Poor? go to the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and learn to Improve your own Wealth. What Bishop <hi>Williams</hi> would say of King <hi>James,</hi> that I may of the <hi>Hollander,</hi> when Lively Described, there is not that thing that a Man or Nation need to <hi>Learn,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:40895:5"/> that they cannot <hi>Teach.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I can wish thee no more Pleasure in the Reading, than I had in the Review of these solid Remarques, when all <hi>Holland</hi> came to me, as the whole World comes to it, even when I was in Bed, where I read more in an hour, than I shall see while I live: Happy that man that goeth over in one Morning the Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys of many yeares, and enjoyes at Night, in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collection and contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Content of an Age. There groweth nothing in
<pb facs="tcp:40895:5"/>
               <hi>Holland,</hi> yet there is the Wealth of the World: here is nothing of my own, and yet here is the substance of what can be said of that Subject; here is for twelve pence, what cost those Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors their Estates; the <hi>Hollander</hi> ever affords good penny worths, and now is one; Twelve pence a piece, and welcome Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:40895:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40895:6"/>
            <head>A DESCRIPTION OF Holland, And The DUTCH Provinces.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou are well met this morning, I pray what newes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R. R.</speaker>
               <p>The best newes that is, (as the <hi>Italian</hi> saith) no newes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>But do you not hear what the House did to day?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:40895:7"/>
               <speaker>R. R.</speaker>
               <p>Neither have I heard, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it fit I should, it was never well in this Kingdom, as Cardinal <hi>Wolsey</hi> observed, since publick de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates were made the subject of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate discourses; but the wisdome of this Government hath better provided that none of the great Consultations of that most August and solemn Assembly in the World, should be published without Their leave.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>Very fit it is that people should study to be quiet, and follow their own business; the neglect of this last makes men <hi>Idle,</hi> and the times bad; that of the first makes them turbulent, and the times dangerous. But did you not hear of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Warre Voted yester<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R. R.</speaker>
               <p>Why that is it—there cannot a Vote pass at <hi>Westminster</hi> for the removing of the obstructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Trade, but it is cryed at <hi>London</hi> a <hi>Dutch Warre:</hi> with so little judgement do we discourse
<pb facs="tcp:40895:7"/> things who are at a distance that it were our greatest prudence not to judge of them at all; but leave those things that are above our le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel as improper for our considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is rather distracted than informed by those halfe thoughts of things, all whose cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances come not under our cognizance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>What was it then that was Voted, if not the <hi>Dutch</hi> Warre?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R. R.</speaker>
               <p>It was Voted by the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blest Patriots that ever sat within those Walls, <q>That all obstructions of Trade should be removed; and particularly that the injuries and affronts done us by the <hi>Dutch</hi> should be enquired into and remedied by all meanes possible, and that they would stand by his most Excellent Majesty in this enquiry and reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy with their Lives and Fortunes.</q>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>What should be the reason of this War proceeding towards them in this juncture?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R. R.</speaker>
               <p>That you must excuseme
<pb facs="tcp:40895:8"/> in, it being as much as every man can do to give a reason of his own actions: this is visible, Trade is decayed; and there is not a Prince more knowing in the Concernes, nor more tender of the interest of Trade in the Christian world then our Dread Soveraign.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>But if it should come to a Warre, is this a proper juncture of time for it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R. R.</speaker>
               <p>Leave that to the exact wisdome of our Superiors, who as they are higher, so they see fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then we: But the <hi>Dutch</hi> were never worse provided then now, so much they are engaged other wayes by Sea and Land; nor we better; So many superfluous hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours have we to spend upon that Warre, that are troublesome to themselves, and us in a time of peace: for Trade we are agreed with all Forreign Nations; against the <hi>Dutch</hi> we are agreed among our selves: never was any thing so una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimously applauded by men of all
<pb facs="tcp:40895:8"/> perswasions and interests, as a <hi>Dutch</hi> Warre, which is the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal Wish of the people; if it were as well the resolve of their Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>I perceive you are reser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved as to any further search into the bottome of this business; will <hi>you</hi> be pleased who are equally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versant in Books, and Men, to give me that light into their Country, Government, Customs, Strength, Treasure, Religion, Trade and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest in the Sea, together with the way they made themselves a free State at first, and that whereby they have preserved themselves since.</p>
               <p>And of any thing that may passe between us of that Subject.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>R. R.</speaker>
               <p>With all my heart, but that my occasions calling me aside, I must remit you to those Persons who have lived upon the place and can best satisfie you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>I pray how many are the United Provinces?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C. B.</speaker>
               <p>Seven, <hi>Viz.</hi> the Dukedom
<pb facs="tcp:40895:9"/> of <hi>Gelder-Land,</hi> the Counties of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zealand,</hi> and the Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships of <hi>Ʋtrecht, Friezland, Overyssel,</hi> and <hi>Groninghen,</hi> and some part of <hi>Brahant</hi> and <hi>Flanders.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>How situated.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C. B.</speaker>
               <p>By the Sea Northward, and by <hi>Germany</hi> Eastward, upon <hi>Cleves, Leige, Flanders</hi> and <hi>Brabant,</hi> South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, if it be not too much pains to you, how do the 17. Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as they call them, lie particularly?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>The seventeen Provinces called <hi>Belgium,</hi> are bounded on the East, with <hi>West-Phalen, Gulicke, Cleve Tryers</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> on the West with the main Ocean, that divides them from <hi>Brittain;</hi> on the North with the River <hi>Ems,</hi> which parts them from East <hi>Friezland,</hi> on the South with <hi>Picardy</hi> &amp; <hi>Champagne</hi> in <hi>France;</hi> on the South-East with <hi>Lorrain;</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Lordship of West <hi>Friezland</hi> the Earldome of <hi>Zuphten,</hi> and the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state of <hi>Groyning, Overyssel,</hi> and part of <hi>Ʋtrecht</hi> added to it of late, they
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40895:9"/> are 1000. <hi>Italian</hi> or 250. <hi>German</hi> miles in compasse; situate under the temperate <hi>Zone,</hi> under the 7, 8, &amp; 9, climates; the longest day in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest of the seventh Climate, being 16 houres, and in the middest of the ninth almost seventeen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>What kind of Aire have they?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>More wholesome then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, partly by the wonderfull increase of the Inhabitants, and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the incredible industry of the people, who by draining the Marsh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and converting the standing wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters into running streams, have pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the Aire of many grosse and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>healthy vapours which did thence usually arise in times foregoing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>How is it inhabited?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>It is competently popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, containing wel-nigh 3. million of men wel-proportioned, great lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of our <hi>English</hi> Beer, unmindful of good turnes and injuries, of good wit for inventing, and of indefatiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble industry in perfecting their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40895:10"/> making of Cloath, Arras, Dornix, Clocks, Watches, the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners Compass, Musick and its In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments, were either invented by them, as were Chariots, Laying on Colours in Oyl, the working of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures in Glass; the making of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steds, Sayes, Tapestries, the making of which, and other Stuffes being driven out of their Countrey by the Duke of <hi>Alva,</hi> they first taught the <hi>English:</hi> The Women generally are of a good Complexion, wel-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portioned, especially in the Leg and Foot, honourers of virtue, active and familiar; both within doores and without, they govern all, which considering the natural desire of Women to bear Rule, maketh them too imperious and burthensome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>What are the Commodities of this Countrey?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>Linnen, Scarlet, Worsted, Sayes, Silkes, Velvets, Armour, Ropes, Cables, Butter and Cheese of which excepting, the two last none Native but <hi>Manufactures,</hi> out
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40895:10"/> of the materials of other Regions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>But what commodity yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them most benefit?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>Herrins and Cod, which they take in the Northern, or the narrow Seas, of the first whereof they make to our shame, besides the Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turers gaines 440000<hi>l.</hi> yearly, and of the last 150000<hi>l.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>VVhat are they most emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent for?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>1. For Navigation, being bred on the Sea from their youth, and knowing no other Countrey, their <hi>Noort</hi> being the fourth that compassed the VVorld, and their <hi>Maier</hi> the first that passed the streight that beareth his name.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>What is the state of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Learning in those parts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>1. The pure Religion and undefiled, was planted there by <hi>Willibrode</hi> an <hi>English</hi> man, 1300. yeares ago; and now is either the Reformed that is countenanced (though other professions are tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated by the Estates general, or the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40895:11"/> Seven Provinces that cast off the Yoke of <hi>Spain;</hi> or the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks which is permited in the Provinces remaining under the King of <hi>Spain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. For Learning, <hi>Erasmus, Lipsius,</hi> the two great <hi>Scalligers, Agncola, Lemnius,</hi> the <hi>Douzas, Ortelius, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator, Cassander, Harmin, Vossim, Grotius;</hi> Natives of this Country, have been the great Restorers of it to the World: and their four Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versities, <hi>Groyning, Herderwiche, Francher,</hi> and <hi>Leyden</hi> profess it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>The Rivers of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try good Sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>The Rivers are chiefly 4. 1. <hi>Rhone,</hi> which rising among the <hi>Grisons</hi> in the <hi>Alpes,</hi> and going by <hi>Constance, Basil, Spire, Wormes, &amp;c.</hi> sends one Stream to the <hi>Maes,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by <hi>Arnem, Ʋtrecht</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> to <hi>Leyden,</hi> a third called <hi>Secle,</hi> through <hi>Ʋtrecht</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> to the Sea between <hi>Dort</hi> and <hi>Rotterdam;</hi> and a fourth called <hi>Yssel</hi> by <hi>Zuphten</hi> and <hi>Daventen,</hi> between <hi>Guelderland</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:40895:11"/> and <hi>Over-Yssel</hi> to the Ocean neer <hi>Amsterdam:</hi> to this River they cast their Children of Old, where if they were legitimated they swimed, if Bastards they sink: 2. <hi>Mosa,</hi> or <hi>Maes,</hi> rising at the Mountaines <hi>Vauge</hi> neer <hi>Lorrain,</hi> sends its streame with a part of <hi>Rhene</hi> by <hi>Grone</hi> and <hi>Dort</hi> to the <hi>Brill,</hi> where it falls with such violence that the water runs fresh for some miles together: 3. <hi>Ems</hi> dividing the two <hi>Friezlands;</hi> 4. <hi>Scaldis,</hi> rising in <hi>Picardy,</hi> and <hi>Artois</hi> into the Sea, a little above <hi>Antwerp.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>How do they secure their Levell and Marsh grounds from the Sea?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>The Shore is much worn in <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zealand,</hi> where it is now defended with Banks and Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires painfully made, and charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably maintained, being ten Ells in heighth, and 25. in bredth, at bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome made of the hardest Clay that can be gotten, in the inside stuffed with Wood and Stone, on the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40895:12"/> covered with Mats, strong and thick made.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>How do you divide the Seventeen Provinces?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>I divide them either,</p>
               <p>I. As Anciently, into two Bishop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricks: 1. <hi>Leige or Luikhe,</hi> 2. <hi>Cambray.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Into Four Dukedomes, 1. <hi>Lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> 2. <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> 3. <hi>Guelder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> 4. <hi>Brabant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Into One Marquisate, <hi>viz.</hi> Of the <hi>Holy Empire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Into Seven Earledomes, 1. <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> 2. <hi>Artois,</hi> 3. <hi>Hainalt,</hi> 4. <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor,</hi> 5. <hi>Zuphten,</hi> 6. <hi>Holland,</hi> 7. <hi>Zealand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Into Five Baronies, 1. <hi>West-Friezland,</hi> 2. <hi>Ʋtrecht,</hi> 3. <hi>Over-Ysel,</hi> 4. <hi>Machlin,</hi> 5. <hi>Groyning.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>II. As Now: 1. Into the 11. Provinces under the King of <hi>Spain;</hi> 1. <hi>Flanders,</hi> 2. <hi>Artois,</hi> 3. <hi>Hainalt,</hi> 4. <hi>Cambray,</hi> 5. <hi>Namour,</hi> 6. <hi>Luxen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> 7. <hi>Limburgh,</hi> 8. <hi>Luikhe</hi> or <hi>Leige,</hi> 9. <hi>Brabant,</hi> 10. the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisate,</hi> 11. <hi>Machlyn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. Into the six under the States
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40895:12"/> of <hi>Holland; viz.</hi> 1. <hi>Holland,</hi> 2. <hi>Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> 3. <hi>West-Friezland,</hi> 4. <hi>Ʋtrecht,</hi> 5. <hi>Over-Ysel,</hi> 6. <hi>Guelderland, Zuph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten</hi> and <hi>Groyning.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>How doth <hi>Holland</hi> lie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Holland</hi> quasi <hi>Hollow Land,</hi> from its Bogs, or Hoyland from its hay hath <hi>Zuiderzee, Ʋtrecht,</hi> and some part of <hi>Guelderland</hi> on the East; the <hi>German</hi> Ocean on the VVest <hi>Zealand</hi> and <hi>Brabant</hi> on the South, and lieth so low that <hi>Ramparts</hi> only keep it from Inundation, and its Industry by infinite Dikes and Channels from being uninhabitable in compasse 180 miles every part of it within 3. hours journey from the Sea; divided to South and North <hi>Holland,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining 23. walled Towns, and 400. Villages.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>Your description of North <hi>Holland?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>North <hi>Holland</hi> lieth between the <hi>Rhine</hi> and the <hi>Zuiderzee,</hi> and hath in it, 1. <hi>Amsterdam</hi> a rich mart and haven Town that can buy 300. sayle of Commodities in six hours,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40895:13"/> and seeth a 100. Ships going in and out at a Tide; scituate on the Gulph <hi>Tie,</hi> and the Channel <hi>Amstel</hi> (whence <hi>Amsteldame</hi>) built in Piles like <hi>Venice</hi> famous for its old Towns and new VValls; for its great variety of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and more of Trade since the decay of <hi>Antwerp:</hi> 2. <hi>Alkmar</hi> famous for its sence, its Butter &amp; Cheese, &amp; eminent for the defeat the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants gave the Duke D'<hi>Alva,</hi> meerly because he had left them no way to escape: 3. <hi>Harlem</hi> a pleasant City on the <hi>Meer,</hi> where <hi>Tullie's</hi> Offices was first Printed: 4. <hi>Nanden</hi> and its strong Castle: 5. <hi>Enchuisen</hi> a Town on the point of the Gulph <hi>Zuiderzee</hi> that was serviceable in the first revolt in cutting off the sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies of <hi>Amsterdam:</hi> 6. <hi>Zurin</hi> and its rich Haven and many Dikes: 7. <hi>Edam</hi> and its Ships and Cheese: 8. <hi>Medemlecke</hi> and its excellent Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storage, though unwalled, yet enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the privilege of a walled Town.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>A word of South <hi>Holland?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>South <hi>Holland</hi> lieth next to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40895:13"/> the middle Channel of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> (passing from <hi>Ʋtrecht</hi> to <hi>Leyden</hi>) and <hi>Zealand,</hi> and is eminent for these Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: 1. <hi>Dort,</hi> a large, <note n="a" place="margin">Former<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly a stabl<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish Wines.</note> rich and well peopled Town, an Island of late no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for its Synod 1618. about the <hi>Arminian</hi> Tenets: 2. <hi>Gorichem,</hi> rich by its daily market of Butter and Cheese, and eminent for its fair Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle and high Steeple, from whence you see 22. walled Townes, besides a number of Villages: 3. <hi>Rotterdam</hi> a strong, fair, wel-traded Town on the Dike, <hi>Ratter</hi> and <hi>Erasmus</hi> his birth place: 4. <hi>Schoon</hi> haven on the <hi>Lecke,</hi> and its fair haven: 5. <hi>Goud</hi> well fortified on the River <hi>Yssel,</hi> one of the sixth principal Townes: 6. <hi>Outwater:</hi> 7. <hi>Ysselstain</hi> eminent for Cordage: 8. <hi>Leiden</hi> an University 1564 that hath a strong <note n="b" place="margin">Built t<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ey say by <hi>Hengist</hi>
                  </note> Castle, 41. Islands, 104. stone Bridges, and 40. wooden: 9. Old <hi>Viawen:</hi> 10. <hi>Heus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den:</hi> 11. <hi>Lerdum:</hi> 12. <hi>Delph</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">1 Who whose said that he was <hi>Christ.</hi> 2. that his Doctrine and not the Law or Gospel could save men. 3. That he had been kept in a place unknown. 4 That he was to restore <hi>Israel,</hi> not by death or tribulation, but by <hi>Love</hi> and grace; binding his Disciples, 1. to conceal his name, 2. his descent, 3. not to discover his Religion to any man in <hi>Basil.</hi> When he died 1556. his Goods were confiscate, and his Bones ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up and burnt.</note>
                  <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid George</hi> birth place, whose Churches are goodly, Streets speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, cloathing-trade considerable.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:40895:14"/>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>Is not the <hi>Hague</hi> one of the Cities?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>No, it chooseth rather to be the Village (though very large as containing 2000. Housholds, in <hi>Gucciardines</hi> time) then the second City, and is famous for the resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the States general, neer which is <hi>Egmond</hi> and the <hi>Arx Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> which <hi>Caligula</hi> erected when he drew up his Army in Battle array to take <hi>Cochleshels.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>Methinks I hear not <note n="a" place="margin">Or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</note> yet of the Cautionary Towns delivered to the <hi>English</hi> 1572?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>They are <hi>Brill</hi> and <hi>Flushing,</hi> lying in one of the six Islands belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to <hi>Holland</hi> called the <hi>Vourne,</hi> which we chose for the command they had on the passage to <hi>Gerteu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:40895:14"/> and the rest of <hi>Brabant,</hi> as also on <hi>Delfe, Dort, Rotterdam,</hi> with the Isles <hi>Weerengeh,</hi> and <hi>Texel</hi> that safe and capacious Bay.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>I pray proceed to <hi>Zealand.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zealand</hi> consisteth of seven Islands, the remainder of Eighteen, the Sea hath swallowed up, and in them 300. Townes, and is divided on the West from <hi>England,</hi> by the Ocean from <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Brabant</hi> by the right and left branch of the River <hi>Scheld</hi> from <hi>Holland</hi> by the <hi>Flache,</hi> containing eight Towns, and an 100. Villages; the Aire unwhole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some, the water salt, the Land good for Pasture, Corn, Mador and Cori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander, Wood scarce, the defect whereof is supplied with <hi>Holland</hi> Turfes, and <hi>Scotch</hi> Coales.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>Which are the seven Islands?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>1. <hi>Walcheren</hi> Southwest of <hi>Sluis,</hi> 10. <hi>Dutch,</hi> and 40. <hi>Italian</hi> Miles round, having the strong, capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious &amp; fair <hi>Middleburgh</hi> in it, which since <hi>Antwerps</hi> decay is an <hi>English</hi> Emporium; 2. <hi>Flushing</hi> the Key to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40895:15"/> the Netherlands, and one of our Cautions till <note n="b" place="margin">When it was by King <hi>Ja.</hi> delivered up, the E. of <hi>Leicest.</hi> Sir <hi>Philip Sidneys</hi> brother then Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour.</note> 1616. 3. <hi>Ramme</hi> and its fair Haven, whence 500. Sayle set out at a time; 4. <hi>Vere,</hi> whence the right Honourable the Earle of <hi>Oxfords</hi> Family.</p>
               <p>2. South <hi>Beverland,</hi> between <hi>Walcheren</hi> and <hi>Brabant,</hi> 20. <hi>Dutch</hi> Miles compass before the Sea im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired it; having in it <hi>Tergoes</hi> Northward, a strong well pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileged Town; 2. <hi>Romerswall</hi> East<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, an Island preserved with much charge; a Woody Country, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant for Hunting and Hawking.</p>
               <p>3. <hi>Poor</hi> and <hi>Overflowed,</hi> North <hi>Beverland</hi> between South <hi>Beverland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>4. Little <hi>Wolfers, Dihe, Schowen,</hi> and two Villages, these are its Western Islands.</p>
               <p>5. <hi>Schowen,</hi> 6. <hi>Dutch</hi> Miles round, wherein are 1. the Salt and <hi>Mader</hi> Town <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lemnius</hi> the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losopher and Phisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive place.</note>
                  <hi>Sirickzed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>6. <hi>Duve,</hi> or <note n="d" place="margin">From the Doves in it.</note>
                  <hi>Doveland,</hi> between <hi>Schowen</hi> and <hi>Tolen,</hi> 4. <hi>Dutch</hi> miles, with much charge preserved with its Farmes and Villages.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:40895:15"/>
               <p> 7. <hi>Tollen,</hi> from the <hi>Eorts Toll</hi> paid in its chief Town, and Saint <hi>Marcius</hi> his <hi>Dyke;</hi> these are the Eastern Islands?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>Of West <hi>Friezland</hi> briefly?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>West <hi>Friezland</hi> hath on the East <hi>Groylingland</hi> and <hi>Westphalen:</hi> On the South <hi>Overyssel</hi> and <hi>Zuider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zee, N.</hi> and <hi>W.</hi> the Sea. The Water, Aire, and Fire are unhealthy or defective here; the Pasture and Cattel very good. It containes first, <hi>Westergoe</hi> with its <hi>Francher a Schola, Illustry, Slaveren</hi> a Hanse Town, <hi>Harlington</hi> a good Haven, and <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che</hi> a fair Town. 2. <hi>Ostrego,</hi> with 1. Len-warden and its Chancery Court; two Dockes neer <hi>Groyning, Frisius</hi> his Birth place; 11. Towns, 345. Villages in all; to this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince belongeth the Isle of <hi>Sche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lincke,</hi> where they take the <hi>Dog-fish</hi> thus, The men dance in Beasts Skins, and the Fish taken with the sport come out of the water, between whom and the water they set their Trayls and catch them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:40895:16"/>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>Shall I intreat your infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation concerning <hi>Ʋtrecht.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ʋtrecht</hi> hath on the East <hi>Guelderland,</hi> on the West, North, and South <hi>Holland,</hi> more fruitfull and dry then <hi>Holland,</hi> containing 70. Villages, 5. walled Towns; <hi>viz.</hi> 1. <note n="a" place="margin">supposed to be <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tavodu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum</hi> spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of in <hi>Tacitus</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Wicke</hi> well built and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, on the midle channel of the <hi>Rhine;</hi> 2. <hi>Rhenen</hi> and its Turfes; 3. <hi>Armesfort</hi> on <hi>Ems;</hi> 4. <hi>Montfort</hi> on <hi>Yssel</hi> strong and pleasant; 5. <hi>Ʋtretch,</hi> called <hi>Ʋltra trajectum,</hi> from the Ferry there, with its fair Churches and Monasteries, its well contrived Houses and Vaults, and its wonderful scituation within a dayes journey of fifty Walled Towns.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Over-Yssel</hi> I suppose is founded on the East with <hi>Westphalen;</hi> on the West with <hi>Zuiderzee;</hi> on the North with <hi>West-Friezland;</hi> on the South with <hi>Guelderland:</hi> a plain Morish Country, divided to <hi>Tuent, Yssel</hi> and <hi>Drent,</hi> containing 11. towns, and an 100. Villages, whereof the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40895:16"/> chief are, 1. <hi>Daventer,</hi> 2. <hi>Swoll,</hi> two strong Hanse Townes on the <hi>Yssel,</hi> taken by the Earle of <hi>Leicester</hi> 1586. 3. <hi>Emen</hi> a large fair and inaccessible Town, 4. <hi>Oldensel,</hi> 5. the Castle <hi>Vallen hoven,</hi> standing on the <hi>Zuider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zee,</hi> the residence of the Governour and the Councell. But please you to instruct me concerning <hi>Guelder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Zupbten</hi> and <hi>Groyning.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Guelderland</hi> bounded on the East with <hi>Cleveland</hi> and <hi>Zuphten,</hi> on the West with <hi>Holland</hi> &amp; <hi>Ʋtrecht,</hi> on the North with <hi>Over-Yssel</hi> and the <hi>Zuiderzee,</hi> and on the South with <hi>Brabant</hi> and <hi>Gulicke;</hi> is flat, Woody, and fruitful; and divided 1. to <hi>Velune</hi> within <hi>Zuiderzee</hi> and the <hi>Rhine;</hi> barren, but healthful and populous; 2. to <hi>Betuwe</hi> between the <hi>Rhine</hi> and <hi>Wael</hi> (so fruitful that there was a <hi>Guelderland</hi> Bull sold in <hi>Antwerp</hi> Ao. 1570. that weighed 3200. pound:) containing 300. Villages and 16. Walled Towns; as 1. <hi>Nimegent,</hi> (in <hi>Latine Novioma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus,</hi>) an Imperial Town, &amp; one of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40895:17"/> sieges of the Empire, that had liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to Coyne for a Glovefull of Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per offered at <hi>Aix</hi> or <hi>Aquisgrave;</hi> well fortified and peopled under whose jurisdiction are, 2. <hi>Trel,</hi> 3. <hi>Bemel,</hi> 4. <hi>Gheut,</hi> 5. the Fort St. <hi>Andrews,</hi> 6. <hi>Rivermond</hi> on <hi>Ruer,</hi> as it falls to the <hi>Maes,</hi> well peopled, and strong by art and nature; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving under its jurisdiction six more Towns, whereof strong, <hi>Geldres</hi> that was never conquered is one, and <hi>Arnhem</hi> where is the <hi>Yssel Dort,</hi> or the <note n="b" place="margin">Which <hi>Drusius</hi> to keep his Souldiers from idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness dig'd.</note>
                  <hi>Fossa drusiana</hi> is another, and the <hi>School Horderwiche</hi> a third, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zuphten</hi> Sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zuphten</hi> hath Eastward <hi>Westphalen,</hi> Westward <hi>Velluwe</hi> of <hi>Guelderland,</hi> Northward <hi>Over-yssel,</hi> and Southward <hi>Cleveland;</hi> and hath twelve Cities, whereof <note n="c" place="margin">Zuisden.</note>
                  <hi>Zuphten</hi> (called so because of its Southern situation among the Fennes,) on the shore of <hi>Yssel</hi> hath the River <hi>Berhel</hi> in the middest of it; a Town indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently well built for its private
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40895:17"/> and publick Edifices; before which Sir <hi>Philip Sedney</hi> received his deaths wound.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>The Situation of <hi>Groyning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Groyningland</hi> hath East<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>East-Friezland,</hi> Westward <hi>West-Friezland,</hi> Northward the Ocean, and Southward <hi>Over-yssel,</hi> wedged in between the <hi>Friezlands,</hi> whereof the chief is, 1. <hi>Old havyn,</hi> 2. <hi>Groyning</hi> its self a rich, great, and well built Town between some streames which add to its pleasure and security having absolute power in all causes, Civil and Criminal without appeal.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. <hi>L.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>I have given you too much trouble already, yet willingly would I be instructed how this Country was Governed from time to time untill they were setled a free State?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>They were governed by their respective Earles and Dukes of several Families, untill by Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages and other contracts they fell to the House of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> and after
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40895:18"/> to that of <hi>Austria,</hi> which governed them in a way of Monarchy, onely allowing them their particular pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges and constitutions untill <hi>Philip</hi> the good first, and <hi>Philip</hi> the second of <hi>Spain</hi> afterwards attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the alteration of their constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the hazard of his own Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, and aiming at an absolute command, lost all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>What loss might these six Provinces be to him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>He lost first at <hi>Antwerp</hi> 100000. Crowns for measuring Corn; 2. The Noventate some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times given amounting to 150000. Crowns <hi>per mensem;</hi> 3. Their rich Presents, whereof one to King <hi>Philip</hi> came to 40. millions of Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens; 4. He lost 60000. men, with an infinite number of Shipping which he had at his command; with his greatest Bulwarke against <hi>France,</hi> and his best Card for <hi>England;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides 400000. men, and an hundred millions of Crowns in the gaining of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:40895:18"/>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>I pray how came King <hi>Philip</hi> to loose these Provinces?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charles</hi> the Emperour his Father at his Death commended these people to his kindness as the chief supporters of his State and Glory if pleased, and his ruine if provoked; And they to obtain his favour presented him at his first en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance on the Government with a grant of 40. millions of <hi>Florens,</hi> as before was said; but his ambition and zeal forgot his own Interest, his Fathers Councel, and their kindness; and designed to overthrow the Privileges his Predecessors had granted and sworn to, (<hi>viz.</hi> 1. That no Strangers should govern them; 2. That no Clergy should be landed among them; 3. That no Levies should be made without their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent; And 4. that upon breach of these Privileges and declaration thereof they might chuse a new Prince, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) and make way for an Arbitrary Government.</p>
               <p>To which end envying so base a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40895:19"/> people such liberty, and fearing the Reformation, to gratifie the Popes humour and his own design, he sends Old <hi>Alva,</hi> who had been 60. years a Souldier, with a large Army, a larger Commission, and the Inquisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be their Viceroy, Count <hi>Egmond</hi> the Souldiers Favourite closed with him to his ruine, for he beheaded him a while after; the Prince of <hi>Aurange</hi> opposed him saying, <hi>He had rather be a Prince without an House, then a Count with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an Head.</hi> If these two had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed they had kept out <hi>Alva,</hi> but falling out, the Prince retires to <hi>Nassaw</hi> in High <hi>Germany,</hi> untill <hi>Alva</hi>'s oppressions, cruelties, and inquisition had forced the people to a defensive Warre, wherein Prince <hi>William,</hi> and his brother <hi>Lodowicke</hi> assist them with various success a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Alva, Requiescens</hi> and <hi>Don John</hi> successive Viceroyes untill taking the peoples Oath and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing the pretensions of <hi>Spain,</hi> they were assisted from <hi>England,</hi> so
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40895:19"/> that the <hi>Spaniard</hi> was glad to Treat with them as a Free State, 1609.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>How could they so long withstand so Puissant a Monarchy?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. <hi>H.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>1. By the long Warres they were Disciplined and made active; and indeed it is against the <hi>Spartans</hi> and the <hi>Turkes</hi> rule to wage Warre long with any one Nation.</p>
               <p>2. By their Fortifications, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of one costeth the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> (who hath no plenty of men,) more Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dirers and Money then five pitched fields.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>I have heard that <hi>England</hi> had as much title to the Provinces of <hi>Holland, Hernall,</hi> &amp;c. as <hi>Spain.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>They say indeed that we might rather claime them in right of <hi>Philippa</hi> King <hi>Edward</hi> the thirds Wife, who was the Earle of those Provinces Eldest Daughter, then the <hi>Spaniard</hi> in right of <hi>Margaret</hi> who was onely his younger Daughter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>Which of the two Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land is most considerable, the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish,</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:40895:20"/> or the Commonwealth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>The first is largest, but the last best peopled and Trade, and consequently most rich and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, able to draw 30000. to the Field at an hours warning, and raise 500000<seg rend="sup">l</seg>
                  <hi>per annum</hi> to maintain them; and as an instance for their power at Sea, though the King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> took 108. Ships of theirs one year, yet they could spare an hundred the next for the expedition against <hi>Spain</hi> and its Armado.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>Are these six Provinces under any one Government?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>No, every Province is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute in it self onely, sometimes they consult together, but can do nothing untill their Consultations are approved of by every Province, whose President, Governour and Councellors by order of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spective States manage their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, onely they have a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Councel at the <hi>Hague.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>Are there any Noble men among them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:40895:20"/>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>Not above three Families, who yet live like Clowns, least the high Shoones envy, who hate nothing more then a Gentle-man, observe them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>Which of these Countries send out most Shipping?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P. H.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zealand,</hi> whence you may see 800. Sayle at a time bound for the East, besides as many for the Western and Southern Coasts, besides 2000. Bugsen, Doog-booten, and Crabbins, wherewith they fish for Herrins, Cod and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and make yearly three Voya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: the Towns and Villages a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding in Women and Children that Weave Nets, and men that build Ships.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
               <p>Sir you have seen the <hi>Hague</hi> the most eminent Town of <hi>Holland,</hi> I pray describe it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>W. S.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>Hague</hi> is rich in wealth, pleasant in Gardens, Stately in Buildings, and noble for her Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, having 2500. great Houses, among which there is none more
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:40895:21"/> magnificent then the Court of <hi>Holland</hi> built 1249. by <hi>William</hi> Earle of <hi>Holland,</hi> like a Castle with Dikes and Gates; it is alwaies guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; on the Northside whereof stands a stately Fish-Pond, pleasantly environed with high Trees on <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verberg,</hi> or the Fish-Ponds Hill: within this Building is a Hall of <hi>Irish</hi> Wood, hung with Booksellers, and Painters shops, with Silver-Coat Armours, Trumpets, and Ensignes which hang there in great number, won at <hi>Turne, Hout,</hi> and <hi>Flanders:</hi> there is the Governour of <hi>Holland, Zealand,</hi> and <hi>Westfriezland,</hi> there are the Courts of Justice, the States-Chamber for the Province, and for the Union, whether all Causes are brought by appeal, and finally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined; here resides the Court Fiscall of <hi>Brabant,</hi> the States gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, the Estates of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>West-Friezland,</hi> the Councell of State, the Masters of the Chamber accounts of <hi>Holland,</hi> the Councell of Warre, &amp;c. every of these having their
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40895:21"/> Chambers apart: Hard by there is a Park 1500. Pales long, full of Oakes, Elmes, Ash, and other Trees; on whose Boughes Birds of all sorts Sing sweetly, under which Deeres, Hares and Conies run; Princes, Earles, Lords, Councellors, Advocates, and all sorts of people walk; Not far from this Park are pleasant Lakes at once the pleasure and the profit of that place, not far from that you come to shady walks, that have at once the revenue and the content of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; one hour you meet here the States man and the Merchant grave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly walking, another while the youth pleasantly playing, at a little distance further of time and place the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diery exercising, and by them the VVomen Landring, and if you please to walk a little further, you will see all <hi>Europe</hi> floating on the one hand by water, and carried on the other by Land to this great Mort of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendome for <hi>Trade</hi> and for <hi>intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:40895:22"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of the Civill Government of the Ʋnited Provinces.</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>I Pray how are the United Governed?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C. B.</speaker>
                  <p>Having cast off their Prince, and the three Estates of Nobility, Clergy and Commonalty; the supream Authority is vested in their Nobility and Citizens; and is an Aristocrasy, or a Democrasy, as either of those Interests pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>Are the Clergy wholly excluded?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C. B.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, unless it be in the Province of <hi>Ʋtrecht,</hi> where the Ecclesiasticks are of their Councels.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>Is there no shadow of Monarchy there?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C. B.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, they grant so much executive Power to the Governors
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40895:22"/> of each Province as make them lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle less than Monarchs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>How is <hi>Holland</hi> Governed?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C. B.</speaker>
                  <p>By the Nobility, and the Burgesses of Eighteen Cityes, <hi>Dort, Harlem, Delfe, Leyden, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterdam, Der-Goud, Rotterdam, Gorchom, Scheedam, Schon-Hoven, Brill, Allmar, Horn, Enkusen, Edam, Manacdam, Med-Embliche,</hi> and <hi>Purmerent;</hi> which do at once over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power the Nobility and engage the whole Commonalty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>How is every particular City Governed?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C. B.</speaker>
                  <p>1. By yearly Burgomasters which manage the Government; 2. The Sheriffes and Scout masters, that administer justice in Causes Criminal and Civil; The Treasu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer that ordereth the Revenue; and the Doctors Advocates or Pension<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers that are of Councell.</p>
                  <p>2. By a general Councell of Justice to whom they appeale from the respective Magistrates.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>No appealing from that Councell.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:40895:23"/>
                  <speaker>C. B.</speaker>
                  <p>No, but there may be more Judges added, and the Case re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viewed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>How are their general Affaires managed, and their Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sury disposed of in the Province of <hi>Holland?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C. B.</speaker>
                  <p>By the Assembly of the Estates called three or four times a year, and made up of one Advocate and one Pensioner, of each of the Eighteen Cities, and the Nobility, who as one City tied together by the rule of right rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and the publick good unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mously agree in all publick Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes, the lesser part being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by the major, without force which availes not among them who are equal in liberty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>Who executes their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, and disposeth their Money?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C. B.</speaker>
                  <p>Another Assembly depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by them to put in execution their Orders, and to call them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether when there is occasion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>What Power hath the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40895:23"/> Governour of <hi>Holland?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C. B.</speaker>
                  <p>Much honour and power: the Militia is at his dispose, their safety depends on his Care, of three men they propose he names all Officers; and any fault he may pardon; wherefore his respect is no less than that of a Prince.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>Are all the other Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces so Governed?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C. B.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, save that the popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy is more prevalent in some pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces than in others, and that some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times one Governour commands two or three Provinces.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D L.</speaker>
                  <p>But how is the Union of all the Estates Governed?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C. B.</speaker>
                  <p>By a general Assembly of the Estates of the seven Provinces consisting of the Nobility and the City Deputies.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>How and when are they called?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C. B.</speaker>
                  <p>They are called by a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty standing Councell, which they leave to execute their Decrees by Summons to each Province, onely
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:40895:24"/> when such Grand Affaires are on foot, as concern the Interest of the whole Union, as Warre, Peace, Truce, making or breaking Leagues, laying on, or taking off new Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>How do they debate things?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C. B.</speaker>
                  <p>The Deputies of each Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince by way of Committee debate matters among themselves, and then give their Votes not as parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular men but as representatives, so that there are but seven Votes of the seven Provinces in all, who must all agree before any matter be concluded.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>But what if some Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces differ?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C. B.</speaker>
                  <p>They depute some Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Assembly to perswade them to yield their private Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and concerns to common in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest and reason.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>What become of their Resolves?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C. B.</speaker>
                  <p>A Councell of State made
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:40895:24"/> up of the Deputies of each Province is appointed by the States general to represent them to put their Decrees in execution, and upon any emergent Difficulty to inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate the necessity of the general Assembly, this Councell is called the Councell of the States general; and as the great Assembly is distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished to seven Votes according to the seven Provinces it repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sents, and guided by a President Weekly chosen out of each Province.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>Are there any more Councels there?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C. B.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, three more under this Councel of the States general; <hi>Viz.</hi> 1. One of State to manage the Army, and its pay by Land, some of whose Members alwayes attend the General; and are ordered to assist in the resolutions of highest concern to the Union, and is made up of Deputies; 2. Another of the common Treasury of the Union; 3. A third of the Admiralty which
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:40895:25"/> manageth their maritime affaires and Incomes, consisting of six Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, four whereof are in <hi>Holland,</hi> one in <hi>Zealand,</hi> and one in <hi>Friez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> these Councels are frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charged according to the consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of each Province.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>Is there no one person over all these Councels?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C. B.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, the Prince of <hi>Aurange,</hi> who hath the chief management of their Forces by Sea and Land.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>Where do these Councels sit?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C. B.</speaker>
                  <p>Mostly at the <hi>Hague,</hi> which is most conveniently situated to diffuse Advisces, Orders and Laws, to fill the Provinces.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>How fitly is the particular Government of each Province proportionated to the general Government of all; and that to the particular interests of each Province; by what conformity and mutual knots of government the united Provinces are tied together, and jointly concur in what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40895:25"/> the common Interest?</p>
                  <p>But is it much altered from their former constitution?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C. B.</speaker>
                  <p>As little as can be, rather by augmenting each Councel to oblige all parties, than by alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any to confound them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>My Ingenious Friend, that saw their Countrey, what think you of their Government?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. <hi>F.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>The Countries Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is popular, and there had need many to rule that Rabble: Tell them of Monarchy but in jest, and they will cut your throat in earnest; the very name they think beares tyranny in its forehead; and they hate it more than a <hi>Jew</hi> doeth Images, a Woman old age, or a Non-conformist a Surplice, not a man among them hath authority by Inheritance, for that were the way in time to parcel out their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try to Families: they are chosen Magistrates, as the King chuseth Sheriffes, not for their Wit but Wealth; which they so over-affect
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:40895:26"/>
                     <hi>that Myne here,</hi> shall walk the Streets as Usurers go to Bawdy-Houses all alone and Melancholly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray informe me what is the strength of the united Provinces?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C. B.</speaker>
                  <p>Their strength is either by Land or by Sea.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray Sir what is their Strength by Land?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C. B.</speaker>
                  <p>1. The Sea, the <hi>Mause,</hi> the <hi>Rhein,</hi> the <hi>Yssel,</hi> especially <hi>Zealand,</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> which is made up of Impregnable Islands; and also Low and Moresh, that it is Invincible: the Great Boy of <hi>Europe,</hi> not such another Marsh in the World; a National <hi>Quagmire,</hi> that they can overflow at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure.</p>
                  <p>2. The natural and artificial strength of their Frontier Cities, as Sluce Impregnable for its low Scituation, and strong Fortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; the strong Fort of <hi>Lillo</hi> in <hi>Brabant, Berghen, ap-Zone, Breda, Gatrinburgh, Heusden, Grave,</hi> and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:40895:26"/>
                     <hi>Crevecour,</hi> the Forts of S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. <hi>Andrews Worden, Niminghen,</hi> and <hi>Schinty,</hi> and the <hi>Sconces</hi> on the Rivers; As strong as industry and Nature can make them: every Town hath its Garrison, and the Keyes of the Gates in the night time are not trusted but in the State-House.</p>
                  <p>3. Their Ammunition is plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, their Armes, Engines, and Warlike Instruments ready, their Provision full, the whole Country lying so Linked together, with natural and artificial Rivers that it can furnish each part in a moment.</p>
                  <p>4. Their excellent Discipline, that makes <hi>Holland</hi> the School of <hi>Europe:</hi> and so furnisheth them with vast Armies of home bred Souldiers, and Forreigners to the number of 60000. in the Field, and 30000. in Garrisons; their In-land men are their best Souldiers, they of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zealand</hi> are the best Sea-men; their Forreigners are the best Commanders: they make
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:40895:27"/> use of the <hi>French</hi> for Activity, of the <hi>English</hi> for Valour; of the <hi>Scots</hi> for Subtlety; and of the <hi>Germans</hi> for Order and Discipline: and they keep all way 20000. in Pay; and allow a 1000<seg rend="sup">l</seg>. a day ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary in time of Warr.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>Methinks Warre should undo them?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>O. F.</speaker>
                  <p>Of all the World they are the people that thrive and grow rich by Warre, which is the Worlds ruine, and their support; so strong is their Shipping, so open their Sea, so fortified their Towns and Country, by reason of their Lowness and Irrigulation.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:40895:27"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Of their Ecclesiastical Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>PLease you to proceed to their Ecclesiastical Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>T. S.</speaker>
                  <p>Having at once shaken off the yoke of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> as they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily fell into a Commonwealth on the one hand, so they settled in a Classical way on the other: for the Ministers that promoted their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation being addicted to Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> and his Platform at <hi>Geneva,</hi> established <hi>that</hi> among them, rather as that which suited with their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest and Constitution, than as what corresponded with truth: they cannot have the Primitive Church Government if they would, and our men that pretend to a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity with them, as the reason of their Non-conformity with us, will
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:40895:28"/> not have it thought they could—where every Burgess is a King, its fit every Minister should be a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>But how do they govern their Church?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>T. S.</speaker>
                  <p>1. They that are Supreme in the State, are so in the Church, and they will not endure two Juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions.</p>
                  <p>2. Under them in every Province the Ministers meet, and propose to them what they judge fit to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted.</p>
                  <p>3. In every Province there are sixteen particular Classes, where those matters are considered of that are to be proposed to the General Assembly.</p>
                  <p>4. The General Assembly meets twice a year, the Classical once a month.</p>
                  <p>5. The Ministers are divided to three sorts, 1. Pastors and Doctors, that teach and instruct; 2. Elders, that rule and over-see; 3. Deacons, that dispose of their Mony.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:40895:28"/>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>How do they admit their Ministers?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>T. S.</speaker>
                  <p>After four years study, 1. They Examine, 2. They impose on them a Sermon, and a Discourse upon some Polemical Subjects, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which, with Prayer and Fasting, by the Magistrates consent, they admit them to the Ministry, with the laying on of the hands of the Presbytery.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>How do they maintain them?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>T. S.</speaker>
                  <p>With Pensions, not exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an 100<hi>l.</hi> a year, whereby they keep them within compass, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance, yet providing for their Wives maintenance, and their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens Education.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>What is the Ministers work there?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>T. S.</speaker>
                  <p>1. He prayes; 2. He reads the Word; 3. He explains by way of Exposition, Catechizing, and Preaching; 4. He Baptizeth the Christians Children upon examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Parents and Sureties;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:40895:29"/> upon competent warning given, he administreth the Sacrament of the Lords Supper four times a year, <hi>viz.</hi> the 1. Sunday of <hi>April, July, October,</hi> and <hi>January,</hi> to those who regard the Discipline, and are Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techized every one in his own Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish after 15 dayes warning: and this the people receive sitting or standing by a Table near the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit. 5. He marrieth a Widow with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in six months after her Husbands decease: or a Maid when her Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians allow it after Banes <hi>thrice</hi> asked with Prayer and Exhortation. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver upon a Sunday. 6. Upon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitation, he shall go and visit the sick, and advise how to settle his Estate for this World, and prepare himself for another. 7. He shall accompany the bodies of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, without Prayer, Sermon, or sound of Bell, to the Grave, which must be alwayes in the Churchyard, and not in the Church. 8. He must reside in his Parish Consistory, and assist them in Church censure thus:
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:40895:29"/> 1. By Admonishing, 2. By Exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from the Lords Supper; and at last by Excommunication, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they proceed thus: The first Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day they pray for the man, naming neither his person nor fault: the second they name his person, but not his crime: the third, the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son is named, his offence published, and he excommunicated, not to be received but upon sincere Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, testified by a reformed Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation, whereof the people are told one Sunday by the Minister, and the next by the Penitent him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, declaring his Confession before the Pulpit. 9. He presides in the Consistory, to gather Voices, to pronounce sentence, to keep the order of debates, to refer greater matters to the greater Assemblies, to register their Acts; to denounce their sentence, and conclude all with Prayer; and this every Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day. 10. The Ministers are delega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Parochial Consistories, to be in the Classical Assemblies, and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:40895:30"/> by the Classical Assemblies, to be of the Provincial Synod: and by the Provincial Synod upon extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary occasions, (as that of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrancy, Controversie, and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevells</hi> Rebellion, in pursuance at <hi>Dort</hi> of it) for a General Meeting, advertizing each other before hand, what is likely to be proposed in the General Assembly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>How is the Lords Day ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>T. S.</speaker>
                  <p>Two Sermons they have upon it, in their rather handsome, than Magnificent Churches, but the peoples noise in playing, especially at theit <hi>Kirhe masts</hi> or <hi>Wakes,</hi> drowneth that of the Minister in preaching. In the Morning they are close and demure, but in the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon their shops fly open, their wheel-barrows go up and down the streets, and they are in the heat of their business.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>What Religion do they countenance?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>T. S.</speaker>
                  <p>They countenance only
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:40895:30"/> Calvinisme, but for Trades sake they <hi>Tolerate</hi> all others, except the Papists, which is the reason why the treasure and stock of most Nations is transported thither, where there is full Liberty of Conscience: you may be what Devil you will there, so you be but peaceable: for <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterdam</hi> is an <q>University of all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions, which grow here confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sedly (like stocks in a Nursery) without either Order or Pruning. If you be unsettled in your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, you may here try all, and take at last what you like best; If you fancy none, you have a Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern to follow of two that would be a Church to themselves: It's the Fair of all the Sects, where all the Pedlars of Religion have leave to vend their Toyes, their Ribbands, and Phanatique Rat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles: their Republick is more to them than Heaven; and God may be more safely offended there than the States General.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:40895:31"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>The</hi> Dutch <hi>Customes.</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>HOw is it the <hi>Dutch</hi> are alwayes gainers by War?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. P.</speaker>
                  <p>1. It increaseth their Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, stirring them to exceed their Adversaries by Sea, as far as he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth them by Land, threatning his <hi>Indies,</hi> and blocking his Havens, while he assaults their Country: for (besides their general Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions at home, and their aid from abroad (where they are supported to check the <hi>Spanish</hi> Greatness) as his <hi>Indies</hi> furnish him with means to assault, so they supply them with means to defend his Designes upon: <hi>Europe</hi> being diverted to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence in <hi>Asia, Affrica</hi> and <hi>America;</hi> More of them live on the Sea (where dwell whole Families) than on the Land.</p>
                  <p>2. By their Excise, which riseth
<pb facs="tcp:40895:31"/> with their charge, the more mony they pay, the more they receive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, in that insensible, but profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble way: what is Exhaled up in Clouds, falls back again in Showers: what the Souldier receives in pay, he payes in Drink: their very ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, though they hate the State, yet love their Liquor, and pay Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise: the most Idle, Slothful, and and most Improvident, that selleth his blood for Drink, and his flesh for Bread, serves at his own charge, for every pay day he payeth his Sutler, and he the Common Purse.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>What do they most taxe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. P.</speaker>
                  <p>Foreign Beer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1. To limit the excess of foreign impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations: 2. That their Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties may be more vendible: 3. To draw in every man to contribute to the wars, those that would not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise part with a farthing, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly laying out their mony, as they think upon their Lusts, but as the State hath contrived, upon the Publick good: but they have those
<pb facs="tcp:40895:32"/> Commodities in time of War in Gross, which in time of Peace they must take in the Retail. 4. They keep up that Concord by Warr, which would fall asunder in Peace.</p>
                  <p>5. They oblige Foreign Nations by ballancing the <hi>Austrian</hi> Power, which they should disoblige, by Peace with him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>But how do they manage their Wars &amp; Trade at a cheaper rate than others?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. P.</speaker>
                  <p>First, they go with less charge, their Ships requiring fewer men, and those men all sharing in the Design, are contented with courser fare; and as they go through all Difficulties with Patience, so they husband all expences with thrift: nothing like concerning the Commonalty in all Designs.</p>
                  <p>2. They carry abroad no Coyn of their own, furnishing themselves elsewhere: Coyn is the blood of a Commonwealth: but other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities they can spare.</p>
                  <p>3. They carry thence the commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities
<pb facs="tcp:40895:32"/> of one place to another, and are the common <hi>Carriers</hi> of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendome, bringing home the while the most Staple Commodities of each Country:</p>
                  <p>4. They trade there upon the best and most free conditions:</p>
                  <p>5. Their Industry and Prudence having besides got more strength in the <hi>Indies,</hi> than any other people.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>Which way do the <hi>English</hi> keep them under?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. P.</speaker>
                  <p>By commanding the Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row-sea, their Coast and ours.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>How do they keep in their Waters?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>P.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>By strong mounds they keep it in, and by Art they make it ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to their trades and carria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which they convey to and fro very easily, subtilly, and cheaply: yea, the Winds serve them, and an Artificial Engine with one man, shall do the work of an hundred: their Channels are so well contrived, that they are not only Draines to
<pb facs="tcp:40895:33"/> their Ground, High wayes to their Carriages, but Ornaments to their Cities.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. <hi>L.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>What are the <hi>Dutch</hi> for publick works?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B <hi>P.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Very Liberal and Noble, as appears by their stately Streets and Buildings, their pleasant Walks, their planted High wayes, which are fenced with such orderly Hedg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, that the whole Country is but one shady Walk by the River side, a Paradise: they having no useless Common, but what (by the common consent of publick spirited Magistrates and people) is turned to profit or pleasure: when as we have more barren Common than they have Land.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>How do the poor live a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>P.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Every body workes there, and not a man begs but by stealth, rather making signes then speaking, whole Families having starved there because they would not be burthensome.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:40895:33"/>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhat Provision do they make for their sick and aged Poor?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. P.</speaker>
                  <p>So carefull are they, that they make not Beggers by relieving them; that they search their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and upon due examination of their Case,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. They Prentise their Children if they have any, teaching them their Trades freely, and directing them by turnes; suffering them not to loyter, but feeding dispatching, and sending them away presently.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. They have neat and distinct Almes-Houses for Men and VVo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, which a man would think were rather rich Merchants habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions then poor Almsmens dwelings.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. They have VVase-Houses such as Christ-church in <hi>London,</hi> &amp;c. to bring up Orphans in, to Trades, Learning, or what they are most inclined to, for the service of the Commonwealth: providing like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise for their women Portions when of age.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Their Guest-house, for sick and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:40895:34"/> poor men and women are well furnished with all Necessaries, atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, Phisick, and what heart can wish.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Their Dul-houses, or Bedlams, for the distracted; Their Tucht-houses, or Houses of Corrections for the stuborn &amp; idle, are generally fair with all meanes used to reclaime the first to their Wits, the other to their Honesties: the Rents and Governments whereof are in the hands of the publick Magistrates.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. In their Lumbards, or Loan houses, the poor have Mony upon any Pawn for a reasonable rate, <hi>viz.</hi> six in the Hundred, with convenient time of payment.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>A word I pray of their frugality whereby they maintaine all this charge.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. P.</speaker>
                  <p>1. Their Diet is homely, and of every mans own providing; 2. They spend more time then mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney in Drinking, improving that time to business too; 3. They traffick for others Superfluities, but
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:40895:34"/> not their own; 4. Their Apparel is plaine and manlike, alwayes of one fashion; 5. Their ambition is solid for realities rather then ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations to serve the publick State rather then private humours; much better is it (say they) to be <hi>port of Holland in possession then Titu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor King of Jerusalem:</hi> 6. Their Lawes are strictly executed, and no forfeitures left to the corrupt dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posal of an Officer, but all bestowed upon the publick: 7. Usury is a stranger amongst them, every man laying out his estate upon the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Traffick: 8. No Idleness there and so no Thieves, which is more restrained there by Whipping, then here by Hanging: 9. If any man gaines extraordinary by money, the tenth of his gain is the Common-wealths; Usurers escaping not there as here, scot-free: 10. A man un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done by Casualty, they set up again; a man cast into Prison the Creditor must maintain; A man troubled with a shifting Adversary, a quick
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:40895:35"/> tryal relieves: 10. Add to this the blessing of God, which they implore before any consultation upon extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary State matters, upon their <hi>Bid-dayes</hi> as they call them: 11. All men debate, and all contribute to the publick Affaires as concerned both by advice and purse: 12. Their Resolutions are secret and sudden: 13. They allow all Opinions at home, and converse with all men abroad for the publick benefit; maxime being to winke at singular inconveniences to avoid universal mischiefes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>Would it be any advantage to us to observe their wayes?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. P.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, for we see where-ever they settle in <hi>England,</hi> as in <hi>Norwich,</hi> &amp;c. the Government of that place is most strict; the people within 20. mile most employed, our Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures best improved, and the poor best provided for: for where the <hi>Dutch</hi> are they relieve our poor, and we never are troubled with theirs.</p>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:40895:35"/>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="riddle">
                              <head>A RIDLE.</head>
                              <p>The Lyon slept securely while the Hunters laid their toyles for him, the Pismire stung and awaked him; he starts up resolutely and checks the presumptuous Pismire; the Pismire cried, my <hi>Lord look about you;</hi> He did so, and spread the snare of the Hunters, he broke it, &amp; securing all avenues at Home, he looks abroad, and saith, <hi>Laesa patientia fit furor;</hi> abused patience turnes fury.</p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. <hi>L.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>I pray what are the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental constitution of their State?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. P.</speaker>
                  <p>1: That no Countess mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry without the States good liking.</p>
                  <p>2. That all Officers be Natives.</p>
                  <p>3. That the Estates assemble at pleasure.</p>
                  <p>4. No impositions be raised or removed but by publick consent.</p>
                  <p>5. That all publick Writings should be in <hi>Dutch.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>6. That their Coyn be disposed of by a Commitee of Merchants.</p>
                  <p>7. That none sell his Possession without publick consent.</p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:40895:36"/>
                  <p> 8. That no Offices be Hereditary.</p>
                  <p>9. That every place should be competently salaried.</p>
                  <p>10. That no man serve a forreign Prince without leave.</p>
                  <p>11. That there be an yearly esti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate of Estate and Persons.</p>
                  <p>12. That there be constant allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance for Residents, Agents, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>13. That every City be Fortified and Garrisoned.</p>
                  <p>14. That none be forced to serve out of his Province.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>What are the reasons that we had to assist them at first?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. P.</speaker>
                  <p>First, the security of the Protestant Religion against the Pope: Second, Of <hi>England</hi> against <hi>Spain,</hi> whom we chose rather to engage in his own Country, then in ours: Thirdly, The opening of Trade, encroached upon by the <hi>Spaniards:</hi> Fourth, The ballancing of <hi>Europe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. <hi>L.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>1. When they steal away our Coyn; 2. When they engross our trade, &amp; bringing it to that pass that we break by hundreds.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:40895:36"/>
                  <speaker>D. <hi>L.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>What were the Reasons in brief for the <hi>Hollanders</hi> Revolt from the King of <hi>Spain?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B. <hi>P.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>1. The breach of their Privileges, which, that King swore either to observe, or quit his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>2. <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth and his Son <hi>Philip</hi> the Second's design to new model their Government.</p>
               <p>3. The Novenal Aid of 800000<seg rend="sup">l</seg>. demand at his Coronation by <hi>Philip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>4. The Kings remote Residence in <hi>Spain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>5. His weak or cruel Substitutes; as the Dutchess of <hi>Parma,</hi> Cardinal <hi>Granvill,</hi> Duke D'<hi>Alva,</hi> the great Commander of <hi>Castile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>6. The inquisition and Bishops designed for those Provinces, <hi>May</hi> the 11. 1565. with power to questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all men for all matters, and swear them to discover one another; the chiefest Nobility and Merchants be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing enrolled in the Black Book.</p>
               <p>7. The neglect of their Petitions.</p>
               <p>8. The <hi>Spainish</hi> Embassadour
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:40895:37"/> D'<hi>Allanaes</hi> Letters taken, wherein it was advised that the Netherlands should be impoverished first, and then kept under; that their Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty should be trepanned, and patriots cut off; that their Priveliges should be declared forfeited; that they should be necessitated to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion and them justly to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed.</p>
               <p>9. <hi>Alva</hi>'s boast that he had 18000. to be executed.</p>
               <p>10. His disarming, impoverishing and engarrisoning the Country in order to those Butcheries of milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he caused afterwards his Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sacks, desolatious, Banishments, and Confiscations.</p>
               <p>11. His keeping of the King at distance from his people.</p>
               <p>12. His suborning of Witnesses, and seting illegal and extraordinary wayes of proceeding.</p>
               <p>13. His seizures of all the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick treasure that paid the poor, the Ministers, the Almes-houses, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>14. His exactions of the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dredth,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:40895:37"/> twentith, and the tenth penny; and so driving all trade out of that Country by his oppressions of the Natives, and his seizures on strangers Goods.</p>
               <p>15. <hi>Don John's</hi> plot by indulging to betray them, discovered in an intercepted Letter of <hi>Don John</hi> wherein all their traines and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod were laid open.</p>
               <p>16. The King of <hi>Spains</hi> disclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of his real right by usurping more, and setting up a Councel of troubles not tied nor limited to any instructions, but invested with liberty freely to give sentence in any thing at pleasure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:40895:38"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>The private Qualities, Condition, and Carriage of the</hi> Dutch.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. <hi>L.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>WHat is the <hi>Dutch</hi> man's private Condition, Quality and Carriage?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>O. F.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Viz.</hi> The <hi>Dutch</hi> are usually of large Statures, handsome and fair Aspects, stronge and able bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, their minds are not less vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous then their bodies; their tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is resolute, their spirit undaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, their nature open and pleasant, their callings beneficial and industri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; their Genious apt to all Arts, especially the Mechanical and Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al: their Ambition is their liberty and privilege, which they have maintained this hundred years with much blood and treasure: their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penses frngal, to the saving of an Egge-shell, they maintaining it for a maxime that a thing lasts longer mended then new: their respects
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:40895:38"/> and considerations are narrow and restrained; their way is active &amp; stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and Provision is made for their necessitous people, but none for the idle, who must work there or they shall not eat; the time they spend is in eating well, and drinking much, and prating most: <q>The truth is (saith my ingenious Author) the compleatest Drinker in <hi>Europe</hi> is your <hi>English</hi> Gallant, there is no such consumer of Liquor as the quaffing of his Healths; the <hi>Dutch</hi> were good at it, but now they have got a custome of pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting over their pots, they sip, and laugh, and tell their tale; and in a Tavern are more prodigal of their time then of their Wine, they drink as if they were short winded, and as it were eat their drink by morsells and let it down by piece meals, rather besieging then assaulting their braines; in a word we are Drinkers, they are soakers; an <hi>English</hi> man is sooner, a <hi>Dutch</hi> man longer drunk.</q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:40895:39"/>
                  <p> Their recreation is warlike, and they are taught to be Souldiers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have attained to be men; Nay (saith my ingenious and noble friend) as if they placed a Religion in Armes, every Sunday is conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the Train-bands marching through the City.</p>
                  <p>They are rather cunning then wise, crafty then cunning, and close then either; their Commonwealth being managed rather by the subtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Trads men, then the policy of States men: their Intelligence is as spreading as their Traffick, and their Traffick as large as the World; there being no Nation under heaven to the bottom of whose Counsels, Interests and concernes they have not insinuated themselves.</p>
                  <p>Their Religion sits loose to them and is their profession rather then their practise, wherein they are too noble a people to be hypocrites, and too civil to be profane, and so pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent as to observe a mean not proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly boasting their Religion as their
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:40895:39"/> shew, but humbly owning it as their duty; they are Jewes of the New Testament, that have changed onely the Law for the Gospel.</p>
                  <p>Their Language though it differ from the higher <hi>Germany,</hi> yet hath it the same ground, and is as old as <hi>Babel,</hi> &amp; although harsh yet of so lof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty signification &amp; so full a tongue, as made <hi>Goropius Becanus</hi> maintain it for the speech of <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradise; <hi>Steven</hi> of <hi>Bruges</hi> reckoneth up 2170 Monosillables which being expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, richly grace that tongue; a Tongue as large as <hi>Europe,</hi> spoken in <hi>Germany, Denmarke, Norway, Sweden,</hi> and <hi>England;</hi> (for most of our old words are <hi>Dutch,</hi>) and so little altered that it is in a manner the same it was 2000. years ago, without the too much mingled bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowings of their Neighbour Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
                  <p>Every thing about them is neat but themselves, the first thing in their houses is a Looking-glass, wherein sure the Landlord seldome
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:40895:40"/> sees his face: their Vessels are mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shalled so orderly as if they were rather for shew then use, ornaments rather then utensils; the <hi>Dutch</hi> mans Building is not large, but neat; handsome on the outside, on the inside hung with Pictures, not Tapistry, he that hath not bread to eat hath a Picture; <q>Were the knackes of all their Houses set to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, there would not be such another <hi>Bartholomew-</hi>Fair in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope;</hi>
                     </q> the <hi>Hogen</hi> paints well yet he ever writes under his sign what it is: His Chambers are but several sand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boxes, and there you must either go out to spit, or blush when you see the Map brought.</p>
                  <p>Their Beds are no other but land Cabines, high enough to need a Lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or staires, up once, you are walled in with Wainscot, and that is (saith my Friend) good discretion to avoid the trouble of making your Will every night, for once falling out else you would break your neck perfectly; But if you die in it, this
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:40895:40"/> comfore you will leave your friends that you died in clean Linnen. Their Habitations are kept handsomer then their bodies, and their bodies then their soules: at first sight you find the And-Irons shut up in Net work, next you have the Warming-pan maffled in <hi>Italian</hi> work, next that the Sconce clad in Cambrick, and like a Crown advanced in the midle of the house.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>You have satisfied me as to their private conditions and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities. I pray what is their Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>O. F.</speaker>
                  <p>1. Clownish and blunt to men, respecting neither person, nor Apparel; they gaze at, and envy, but never reverence a Gentlemen.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>2. Chast and modest to their Women, being strangers to the two fomentors of Lust, idleness and Courtship; alwayes doing less then they speak, and speaking less then they think.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>But their Women have an ill name?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:40895:41"/>
                  <speaker>O. F.</speaker>
                  <p>A <hi>Dutch</hi> Womans full veins and high blood makes her Gamesome but not Mercenary, entertaining Gallants, rather then entertained by them; but if a man once in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick discovereth their private fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, or pretend to any more then is civil, she falls off like a Fairy wealth disclosed, and turnes like beer with lightning to a sowreness, which neither art nor labour can never make sweet again.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. I.</speaker>
                  <p>What is their temper?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>O. F.</speaker>
                  <p>Hardy, head-strong, chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish, and testy, their will is their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, <hi>the Commonwealth God with them;</hi> Warr is their Paradice, peace is their Hell, the <hi>Spaniard</hi> is the Devil they hate; you may sooner convert a <hi>Jew</hi> to Christianity, turn an old Baud Puritan, then convince a <hi>Dutch</hi> man of reason.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>How do these rough hewen pieces model their Commonwealth?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>O. F.</speaker>
                  <p>Not a man of them but may be a States-man, for they have all this gift not to be too nice consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced:
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:40895:41"/> It is a noble Testimony that so grave an Historian as <hi>Tacitus</hi> hath left of them upon record these 1500. years, <hi>deliberant dum fingere nesciunt, constituunt dum errare non possunt.</hi> They deliberat when they cannot dissemble, and resolve when they cannot erre.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>What is their behaviour towards Strangers?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>O. F.</speaker>
                  <p>1. They are seldome decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, for they will trust no body; 2. They may alwayes deceive, for you must trust them as for instances if you travel to ask a bill of Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars is to purre in a Wasps Nests; you must pay what they ask as sure as if it were the assessement of a Subsidy; 3. Complement is an idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, those busie people were never skilled in: they are half Marred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Saylors; &amp; being Souldiers they are quite spoiled, for then they would let a <hi>Jew</hi> build a City where <hi>Harlem-mere</hi> is and after cousen them of it; 4. They shall abuse a stranger for nothing, and after a few
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:40895:42"/> base termes scortch one another to a <hi>Carbonado,</hi> or as they do their Roches when they fry them; 5. They love none but those that do for them, and when they leave off they neglect them; they have no Friends but their Kindred, which at every Wedding feast meet among themselves like tribes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray what is their Carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age among themselves?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>O. F.</speaker>
                  <p>They are all equal, no way to know Master or Mistress but to take them in bed together; it may be those are they; otherwise <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kie</hi> can prate as much, laugh as loud, be as bold, and sit as well as Mistress; your man may be sawcy, and you must not strike him, your Schollar untoward, you must not whip him; the Son asketh his Fathers blessing by clapping him on the back, &amp; bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him good night, &amp; his Mothers by kissing her and saying god-boy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>But how do they look, and go?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>O. F.</speaker>
                  <p>They are their own dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guizes,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:40895:42"/> and their own Cloaths so thick and tanned their faces; their women have good faces e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough if they did not marre them with making their Ear-wyres, and so nipt in their Cheekes that you would <hi>think</hi> some <hi>fairy had</hi> done <hi>them</hi> a mischief, and pinched them behind with tongues; their dressings are so backward that they have much more crown then face: <q>Men and women saith the ingenious Travelour, are Starched so blew, that if once they grow old, you would verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve you saw winter walking up to the neck in a barrel of Indigo; and therefore they raile at <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> for spending no more Blew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; your man among them is else clad tollerably, unless he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines to the Sea fashion, and then are his Breeches yawning at the knees, as if they were about to swallow his Legges unmercifully.</q> The VVomans Hood is close, her breast open; her Gown wide, her Rings many, her little Keyes and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:40895:43"/> Chaines more; and the man and womans fashion is more constant then their faith.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>A word Sir of their meals or diet?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>O. F.</speaker>
                  <p>1. They eat much, and spend little; 2. Roots and stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fish are staple commodities in their houses, and if they have Flesh they can keep it hot more dayes then a Pig in Pye-corner; salt Meates and sowre Cream sugared is their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light.</p>
                  <p>Their Cookery is natural, and an artificial dressing of Meat you can perswade them to neither with love or money; you must have pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience at their Tables to stay till break of day, to pledge every man about you, and to sit with a woman of each side of you, carrying away in the morning it may be instead of Sweet-meates a piece of Apple-Pie in your pocket.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:40895:43"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Our Right to the Narrow Seas.</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>I Pray will you make out what Right we have to the Narrow Seas in few words.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
                  <p>1. The Seas that surrounds our Island, whether the <hi>Scottish,</hi> the <hi>Brittish,</hi> the <hi>Irish,</hi> or <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> were possessed, and secured by the <hi>Brittains,</hi> who fished so much upon them that they burnished the Hilts of their Swords with such Fishes Teeth as they took; and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded so considerably that none came amongst them but Merchant.</p>
                  <p>2. Those Seas were by them transmitted with their Countries to the <hi>Romans</hi> upon the Conquest, who as they managed the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Land by Presidents, so they did that at Sea by an <hi>Archigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernasy,</hi> or chief Governour and Admiral; who secured Commerce, took prizes, looked on the Coasts
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:40895:44"/> of <hi>Spain, Italy,</hi> and <hi>Affrica</hi> it self.</p>
                  <p>3. After the <hi>Romans,</hi> the <hi>Saxons</hi> succeeded to this Right and Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and commanded the Sea un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Count of the <hi>Saxon</hi> shore, <hi>i. e.</hi> (whatever <hi>Panarollus</hi> saith to the contrary) the Sea-shore, <hi>Octa</hi> and <hi>Ebista</hi> under <hi>Vortigerne</hi> and <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gist</hi> commanding these Seas, the <hi>Saxons</hi> and <hi>Danes</hi> keeping a nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Navy to that purpose, by such tributes and duties as they imposed upon their Vassals particularly <hi>Dane-gelt</hi> for the Guard of the Sea; <hi>Edgar</hi> and <hi>Canutus</hi> stiling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves Soveraign of the Sea.</p>
                  <p>4. The Right and Dominion of the Seas passed with this Nation to the <hi>Normans,</hi> as appears 1. From their government, the custody of the <hi>seas</hi> alwaies being under an <hi>admiral</hi> by Commissions from the several Kings maintained by tributes, paid in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration of the said Custody; 2. From their right in all the Isalnds lying on the Sea before the <hi>French</hi> shore; 3. From leave asked alwaies
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:40895:44"/> and granted by Forreigners of the <hi>English</hi> to pass those seas.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray who asked leave?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
                  <p>The Kings of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> and <hi>Sweden,</hi> the Hans-Towns in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time; the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> and <hi>Zealanders</hi> themselves not daring to Fish before they asked leave of <hi>Scarborough;</hi> and King <hi>James</hi> proclaiming <hi>May</hi> 6. 1610. that none Fish upon the <hi>English</hi> or the <hi>Irish</hi> Sea without leave obtained at every year at least renewed, from the Commissioners appointed for this purpose at <hi>London.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But 4. our Right to the Sea ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears from the Limits we set to such Forreigners (as Moderators of the sea) as are at emnity with one another, and at amity with the <hi>English.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>5. From publick Records where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Dominion of the sea is ascri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to the Kings of <hi>England</hi> by the King himself, and the Estates of Parliament, with very great deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration, and in such express words
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:40895:45"/> as these; Lords <hi>Of the English Sea on every side, all people accounted us Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns of the Seas; that our Soveraign Lord the King and his Illustrious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors being Lords of the Seas would impose a tribute upon all stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers: the Kings of</hi> England <hi>have by right of their Dominions been Lords of the Sea: (these are the words of all Europe by their Commissioners at</hi> Paris;) <hi>and made Lawes, Statutes, and restraints of Armes upon them, together with Admiralls that they should preserve their superiority over the same.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>7. From the Laws and most re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Customs of <hi>England that make the Seas</hi> the patrimony of <hi>England; and the King of the old Custome of England, Lord of the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Seas;</hi> and his Soveraignty there so ancient; they make the four Seas to be equivalent with those words within or without the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; <hi>De mer appurtenant au Roy l'Angleterre:</hi> the Sea belonging to the King of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:40895:45"/>
                  <p> 8. From the Coyn called <hi>Rose-Nobles,</hi> of which it is said four things our Noble sheweth to me, King, Ship, Sword, power of the Sea.</p>
                  <p>9. From the Custome of striking sayl upon our Coasts to our Ships time out of mind.</p>
                  <p>10. From the acknowledgement of the <hi>Flemings</hi> and others by sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, to our Kings as Soveraigns of the Sea, since <hi>Edward</hi> the thirds time.</p>
                  <p>11. From the Licenses upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord granted to the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings,</hi> with their limited number of Boates to Fish upon our Coasts.</p>
                  <p>12. From the prerogative where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by all wreckes and royal Fishes, as VVhales, Sturgeons taken in our Seas are due to the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> onely, or unto such unto whom by special charter they have gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the same, stat. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. 17. toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with all things floating upon the said Sea all Flostan, <note n="a" place="margin">Flostan is things that float; Jestan Goods in danger cast out; Ligan all Weights: things sunk.</note> Jestan, and Ligan, as our Lawyers speak.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:40895:46"/>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>How far doth this Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Right of Ours extend?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>I. S.</speaker>
                  <p>All along the <hi>Brittish</hi> Coast as far as the <hi>Mediterranean,</hi> yea the Coasts of <hi>Friezland</hi> by the <hi>Danes</hi> confession, and our claimes, was part of our Royalty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>I thought the Water was as common as the Aire.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>I S.</speaker>
                  <p>No! for the <hi>Jewes</hi> had the Soveraignty of the Waters that washed the Holy Land by the Law of God, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 47. 10. and the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> of the <hi>Mediterraneans</hi> by the Law of Nations, <hi>Plut.</hi> in <hi>Pomp.</hi> King <hi>Minos</hi> claimed <hi>Crete</hi> and its Sea; the seven Nations of the Fast and South commanded those Seas, as the <hi>Lydians,</hi> Lord of the Seas, <hi>&amp;c. Selden p.</hi> 59. the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> the <hi>Phaenicians,</hi> the <hi>Lacaedemonians,</hi> and <hi>Athenians;</hi> the four Emperours were said to be Lords of much Land and of much Sea; and the common enjoyment of it was abolished as an unjust thing by the Eastern constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; the <hi>Venetians</hi> held the <hi>Adri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atique;</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:40895:46"/> the <hi>Genoes</hi> the <hi>Ligusticke;</hi> the <hi>Tuscans</hi> the <hi>Tyrrhene;</hi> and <hi>Rome Tiber,</hi> and the Sea adjoyning.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Portugals</hi> are in antient Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords called Lords of Commerce, <hi>Navigation,</hi> and the Sea; and the <hi>Spainish</hi> of the Firme-land and Oce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an; the King of <hi>France</hi> is declared supream Lord of the Sea that flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth about his Kingdome; as are the <hi>Danes,</hi> the <hi>Swedes,</hi> the <hi>Pole,</hi> and <hi>Turkes:</hi> neither is the Aire less ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate then the Sea; yea the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Hollanders</hi> themselves discounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced <hi>Grotius</hi> and his Book of the communities of the Elements: And to conclude all the foresaid <hi>Venetians</hi> A<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. 1508. in a publick de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate with <hi>Ferdinand</hi> then Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour carried the propriety of the <hi>Adriatique</hi> Gulph.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:40895:47"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>The Inestimable benefit the</hi> Dutch <hi>make of the</hi> Brittish <hi>Seas.</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>WIll you shew me the advantage the <hi>Dutch</hi> make of our Seas?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>I. B.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, our Seas yield inesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable treasure to those that take paines therein all the year; For,</p>
               </sp>
               <p>The Summer Fishing, for Herring beginneth about Midsommer, and lasteth some part of <hi>August.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Winter Fishing for Herring lasteth from <hi>September</hi> to the midst of <hi>N<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vember,</hi> both which extend in place from <hi>Boughones</hi> in <hi>Scotland</hi> to the <hi>Thames</hi> mouth.</p>
               <p>The Fishing for Cod at <hi>Alamby wirlington,</hi> and <hi>White-haven</hi> near <hi>Lancashire,</hi> from <hi>Easter</hi> till <hi>Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sontide.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Fishing for Hake at <hi>Aberdeny, Abv<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>swhich,</hi> and other places be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Wales</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> from
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:40895:47"/>
                  <hi>Whitsontide</hi> to Saint <hi>James-tide.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Fishing of Cod and Ling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Padstow</hi> within the Land, and of <hi>Severn,</hi> from <hi>Christmas</hi> to <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Fishing for Cod on the West part of <hi>Ireland,</hi> frequented by those of <hi>Giscay, Galicia,</hi> and <hi>Portugal</hi> from the beginning of <hi>April</hi> untill the end of <hi>June.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Fishing for Cod and Ling on the North, and Northeast of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> from <hi>Christmas</hi> untill <hi>Michael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Fishing for Pilchers on the West Coast of <hi>England,</hi> from St. <hi>James-tide</hi> untill <hi>Michaelmas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Fishing for Cod and Ling, upon the Northeast of <hi>England,</hi> from <hi>Easter</hi> untill <hi>Midsummer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Fishing of great staple Ling, and many other sorts of Fish lying about the Islands of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and in the several parts of the <hi>Brittish</hi> Seas all the year long.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>To shew the benefit of our Fish trade I pray shew me some in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:40895:48"/>
                  <speaker>J. B.</speaker>
                  <p>In <hi>September,</hi> not many years since upon the Coast of <hi>Devon</hi> shire neer <hi>Minigall</hi> 500. Tun of Fish were taken in one day. And about the same time three thousand pound worth of Fish in one day were taken at St. <hi>Joes</hi> in <hi>Cornewall</hi> by small Boates, and other poor provisions.</p>
                  <p>Our five-men-boates, and Cables adventuring in a calm to land amongst the <hi>Holland</hi> Busses not far from <hi>Robin Hoods</hi> Bay, returned to <hi>Whitby</hi> full fraught with Herrings, and reported that they saw some of those Busses take 10. 20. 24. lasts at a draught of Herrings, and returned into their own Country, 40. 50. and 100. Lasts of Herrings in one Busse.</p>
                  <p>Our Fleet of Colliers not many years since returned from <hi>Newcastle</hi> laden with Coales about the Well, near <hi>Flamborough</hi> head, and <hi>Scarbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough,</hi> met with such multitudes of Cod, &amp; Ling, and Herring, that one amongst the rest with certain ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ookes, and other like Instruments
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:40895:48"/> drew up as much Cod and Ling in a little space of time, as were sold well near forasmuch as her whole lading of Coal. And many hundred of Ships might have been there la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in two dayes and two nights.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray shew me particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the advantages the <hi>Hollanders</hi> make of their Fishing upon our Coasts?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>J. B.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir <hi>John Burroughes</hi> recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned up eight sorts of advantages:</p>
                  <p>1. In Shipping; 2. In Marriners; 3. In Trade; 4. In Townes and Fortifications; 5. In power extern; or abroad; 6. In publick Revenue 7. In private Wealth; 8. In all manner of provisions, and store of things necessary.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>How do they encrease their Shipping by our Fishing?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>J. B.</speaker>
                  <p>Besides 700. Strand boats, 4000. Evars, and 400. Sallits, Dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and Tod-boates, wherewith the <hi>Hollanders</hi> ply upon their own Coasts, every one of those imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing another to fetch salt, and carry
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:40895:49"/> their Fish into other Countries, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in all 3000. Sailes, maintaining and setting on work at least 4000. persons, Fishers, Trades men, Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Children. They have 100. Doyer boates of 150 Tunes a piece, or thereabouts. 700. Pincks and Well-boates, from 60. to 100. tunes a piece; which altogether Fish up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Coasts of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> for Cod and Ling onely. And each of these employ another Vessel for providing of Salt, and transport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their Fish, making in all 1600. Ships, which maintaines and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy persons of all sorts, 4000. at least.</p>
                  <p>For the Herring season they have 1600. Busses at the least, all of them Fishing onely upon our coasts, from <hi>Boughonness</hi> in <hi>Scotland</hi> to the mouth of <hi>Thames.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And every one of these maketh work for three other Ships that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend her; the one to bring in Salt from Forreign parts, another to carry the said Salt and Cask to the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:40895:49"/> Busses, and to bring back their Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rins, and the third to transport the said Fish into forreign Countries: So that the total number of Ships and Busses paying the Herring faire is 6400. whereby every Busse one with another, imployeth forty men, Marriners and Fishers within her own hold, and the rest ten men a piece, which amounteth to 112000. Fishers and Marriners. All which maintaine double, if not treble, so many Tradesmen, Women and Children a land.</p>
                  <p>Moreover they have 400. other Vessels at least, that take Herring at <hi>Yarmouth,</hi> and there sell them for ready money: so that the <hi>Hollanders</hi> (besides 300. Ships before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, Fishing upon their own Shores) have at least 4800 Shipes onely maintained by the Seas of great <hi>Brittain,</hi> by which meanes princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally, <hi>Holland</hi> being not so big as one of our Shires of <hi>England,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taing not above 28. miles in length, and three in bredth; hath encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:40895:50"/> the number of their Shipping to at least 10000. Saile, being more then are in <hi>England, France, Spain, Portngal, Italy, Denmarke, Poland, Sweden,</hi> and <hi>Russia.</hi> And to this num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber they add every day, although their Country it self, affords them neither Materials, nor Victuals, nor Merchandize to be accounted of towards their setting forth. Besides these of <hi>Holland, Lubeck,</hi> have 700. great Ships, <hi>Hamborough</hi> 600. <hi>Emb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> 400. whereunto the Ships of <hi>Bremern, Biscay, portugal, Spain,</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> which for the most part Fish in our Seas; and it will appear that 10000. Saile for forreign Ves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels and above are imployed and maintained by Fishing upon our Coasts. So that in <hi>Holland</hi> there are built 1000 Saile at the least, to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply shipwracks, and augment their store; which as the prime and common Nursery, is the chiefest means onely to encrease their number.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>How do the <hi>Dutch</hi> encrease their Marriners.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:40895:50"/>
                  <speaker>J. B.</speaker>
                  <p>The number of Ships fish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on our Coasts as being aforesaid, 8400. if we allow but twenty per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons to every Ship one with another the total of Marriners and Fishers amounteth to 168000 out of which number they daily furnish their lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger voyages to all parts of the World; for by this meanes they are not onely enabled to brook the Seas and to know the use of the Tackles and Compass, but are likewise in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed in the Principles of Navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, and Pilotage, insomuch as from hence their greatest Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors have had their Education and breeding.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. <hi>L.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>How do the <hi>Dutch</hi> encrease their Trade?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>J. B.</speaker>
                  <p>By reason of these multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of Ships and Marriners they have extended their Trade to all parts of the World, exporting for the most part in all their Voyages our Herring, and other Fish for the maintenance of the same; in exchange whereof they return the several
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:40895:51"/> Commodities of other Countries.</p>
                  <p>From the southern parts, as <hi>France, Spain,</hi> and <hi>Portugal,</hi> for our Herrings they return Oyles, Wines, Pruines, Honey, Wooles, &amp;c. and with store of Coine in <hi>Spain.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From the <hi>Straights,</hi> Velvets, Sattins, and all sorts of Silkes, Allames, Currans, Oyles, and all Grocery Ware, with much money.</p>
                  <p>From the East Countries for our Herrings, and other <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Italian</hi> Commodities before retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, they bring Home, Corne, Wax, Flax, Hemp, Pitch, Tarre, Sope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ashes, Iron, Copper, Steel, Clap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board, Wainscot, Timber, Deale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board, Dollers, and <hi>Hungary</hi> Gilders.</p>
                  <p>From <hi>Germany</hi> for Herrings, and other salt Fish, Iron, Steel, Glass, Milstones, Rhenish Wines, Button<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate for Armour, with other Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, Silkes, Velvets, Rashes, Fustians, Baratees, and such like <hi>Frankeford</hi> Commodities, with store of <hi>Rix-Dollers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From <hi>Brabant</hi> they return for
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:40895:51"/> the most part ready money with some Tapistryes, and Hullship; yea some of our Herring are carried as far as <hi>Brasile.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that which is more strange and greatly to our shame, they have 4 hundred Ships with Fish, in which our men of <hi>Yarmouth</hi> within <hi>Ken,</hi> almost at Land do vent our Herrings amongst us here in <hi>England,</hi> and make us pay for the Fish taken upon our own Coast ready money, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they store their own Country.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>How do the <hi>Dutch</hi> by fish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on our Seas encrease their Townes and Forts?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>J. B.</speaker>
                  <p>By this their large extent of Trade they are became as it were Citizens of the whole World, whereby they have so enlarged their Townes, that most of them within 400. years that are full as great again as they were before; <hi>Amster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, Leyden,</hi> and <hi>Midleburgh,</hi> having been lately twice enlarged, and their Streets, and buildings so fair, and orderly set forth, that for beauty
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:40895:52"/> and strength they may compare with any other in the World, upon which they bestow infinite summes of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; all originally flowing from the bounty of the Sea, from whence by their labour and industry they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive the beginning of all that Wealth and greatness; and particularly for the Havens of the aforesaid Townes, whereof some of them cast 40. 50. or 100000<hi>l.</hi> Their Fortifications also both for number and strength, upon which they have bestowed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite summes of money, may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare with any other whatsoever.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>How do the <hi>Dutch</hi> by Fish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in our Coast encrease their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer abroad?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>J. B.</speaker>
                  <p>Such being then the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Ships and Marriners, and so great their Trade, occasioned principally by their Fishing; they have not onely strengthened and fortified themselves at home, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell all forreign invasions, as lately in the Warr between them and <hi>Spain,</hi> but have likewise stretched
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:40895:52"/> their power into the East, and West-<hi>Indies</hi> in many places, whereof they are Lords of the Sea Coasts, and have likewise Fortified upon the Maine, where the Kings and people are at their Devotion. And more then this, all neighbouring Princes in their differences (by reason of this their power at Sea,) are glad to have them of their party: so that next to the <hi>English</hi> they are now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the most redoubted Nation at Sea of any other whatsoever.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>How do the <hi>Dutch</hi> by Fish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on our Coasts encrease their publick Revenue?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>I. B.</speaker>
                  <p>That may appear in that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove thirty years since, over and above the Customs of other Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize, Excises, Licenses, Waftage and Lastage, there was payed to the State for custome of Herring and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther salt Fish above 300000. pound in one year, besides the tenth Fish, and Cask payed for Waftage, which cometh at the least to as much more among the <hi>Hollanders</hi> onely, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:40895:53"/> the tenth of other Nation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing added it amounteth to a far greater summe.</p>
                  <p>We are likewise to know that great part of their Fish is sold in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Countries for ready money, for which they commonly export of the finest Gold and Silver, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing home recoine it of a baser allay under their own stampe, which is not a small means to augment their publick treasure.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>How do the <hi>Dutch</hi> by Fish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on our Seas encrease their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate wealth?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>J. B.</speaker>
                  <p>That will appear to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great by these following particulars:</p>
                  <p>During the Warrs between the King of <hi>Spain</hi> and the <hi>Hollanders</hi> before the last Truce, <hi>Dunkirke</hi> by taking, spoiling, and burning the Busses of <hi>Holland,</hi> and setting great ransome upon their Fishermen, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced them to compound for great summs that they might Fish quietly for one year, whereupon the next
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:40895:53"/> year after the Fishermen agreed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst themselves to pay a Doller upon every Last of Herrins, towards the maintenance of certain Ships of Warr to waft and secure them in their Fishing, by reason whereof there was a Record kept of the several Lasts of Herrins taken that year, and it appeared thereby that in one halfe a year there were taken 30000. Lasts of Herrins which at 16. 20. 30. pound <hi>per</hi> Last a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounteth to 3600000 and at 16. 20. 30. pound the Last they ordinarily sold, then transported into other Countries, it cometh at least to 5000000 <hi>l.</hi> whereunto if we add the Herrings taken by other Nations, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Cod, Ling, Hake, and the Fish taken by the <hi>Hollanders</hi> and other our Neighbours upon the <hi>Brittish</hi> Coasts all the year long, the total will evidently arise to be above 1000000 <hi>l.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The great trade of Fishing em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying so many men at Sea must necessarily maintaine as great a
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:40895:54"/> number of Trades men and Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers by Land, as Spinners, Hemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winders to make Cables, Cordage, Yarne twine for Nets, Weavers to make Saile Cloaths, Cecive Pachers, Tollers Dressers, and Couchers to sort and make the Herring lawful Merchandize; Tanners to Tan their Sailes and Nets; and Coopers to make Caskes, Block and Bowl ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers for Shipes; Keelemen and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers for carrying and removing their Fish; Sawyers for plantiers, Carpenters, Shipwrights, Smiths, Carmen, Boatmen, Brewers, Bakers, and others that cannot otherwise live with their Wives, Children and Families; every Orphan, Servant, or poor man may venture their stock in Fishing Voyages, which affords them extraordinary encrease, and is duly paid according to the propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their gain.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>How do they encrease their Provision?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>J. B.</speaker>
                  <p>Though there be nothing in <hi>Holland</hi> but Hops, Madder, But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:40895:54"/> and Cheese; yet by fishing they have plentiful of all manner of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vision for necessity, as Corne, Beef, Mutton, Hides, Cloathes; for luxury as Wines, Silkes, Spices, or defence as Pitch, Tarre, Cordage, Timber; all which they have not onely in competent proportion for their use, but are likewise able from their se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Magazines to supply their Neighbour Country.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>Might we not thrive as well as they upon our own Fish?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>J. B.</speaker>
                  <p>We might no doubt, and have those Fish for nothing that we pay them for, repairing thereby 230. small Fisher Towns decayed for want of that improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and adding both honour, strength, and riches to our King and Country, which how easily it may be done will appear by some few Observations following.</p>
                  <p>By erecting two hundred and fifty Busses of reasonable strength and bigness there will be employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made for 1000. Ships, and for
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:40895:55"/> at least 10000. Fishermen and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners at Sea, and consequently for as many Tradesmen, and Labourers at Land.</p>
                  <p>The Herrings taken by the Busses will afford his Majesty 200000 <hi>l.</hi> yearly custome outward; and for Commodities returned inward 30000 <hi>l.</hi> and above.</p>
                  <p>We have Timber sufficient, and at reasonable rates growing in our own Kingdome for the building of Busses, every Shire affordeth har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and able men fit for such imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment who now live poorly, and idle at home.</p>
                  <p>We have Victuals in great plenty sold at easie rates, without payment of Excises, or impost.</p>
                  <p>Our Shores and Harbours are near the places where the Fish do haunt.</p>
                  <p>For Drink, or Nets, salting and packing our fish, and for succour in stress of Weather, we may bring our Fish to Land, salt and pack it, and from some parts of his Majesties
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:40895:55"/> Dominions be at our Markets in <hi>France, Spain,</hi> or <hi>Italy</hi> before the <hi>Hollander</hi> can arrive in <hi>Holland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We have meanes to transport our Fish into some Northern Countries where the <hi>Hollander</hi> seldome or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver come. And though we had as many Busses as the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> yet is their vent for all, or more, for in East and Northern Countries where the <hi>Hollanders</hi> seldome or never come. And though we had as many Busses as the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> yet is there vent for all, or more, for in the East and Northern Countries and in many other places, Herrins are eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry daies meat, winter and summer, as well to draw on drink as to satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie hunger; and in most places the greatest part of the year they be scarce to be had; for presently after <hi>Michaelmas</hi> the <hi>Sound</hi> and Rivers are frozen up, so as no Herrings can be transported into twenty King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and free States untill <hi>July,</hi> which is for thirty weeks space to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, so that when Lent comes
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:40895:56"/> there are few to be bought for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. Lastly, since by care and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustry we gained cloathing from the <hi>Flemmings,</hi> doubtless so by the same meanes we may as easily grow ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert in the art of Fishing, and in time make it a staple Commodity of our own.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>What are the general de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects that hinder our improvement of our Fishing?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>J. B.</speaker>
                  <p>1. General liberty of eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Flesh, contrary to old custome, and the statute Laws provided for observing Fish dayes, from whence our scarcity and dearth of fish pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth; for where Flesh is ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily spent fish will not be bought, and want of sale decayeth all trade, Gaine being the nurse of Industry.</p>
                  <p>2. Want of order and discretion in our fishing, every man being left to himself, and permited to fish as best liketh him; whereas amongst the <hi>Hollanders</hi> two of the best ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced Fishermen are appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to guide the rest of the Fleet,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:40895:56"/> all others being bound to follow them, and to cast their Lines accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their direction.</p>
                  <p>3. The <hi>Hollanders</hi> and other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions set forth with their Busses in <hi>June</hi> to find the Shoale of fish, and having found it, dwell amongst it till <hi>November,</hi> whereas we stay till the Herring come home to our road steads, and sometimes suffer them to pass by ere we look out, our Herring-fishing containing onely seven weekes at the most, and theirs twenty.</p>
                  <p>4. The <hi>Hollanders</hi> Busses are great and strong, and able to brook foul weather, whereas our Cables, Cracsers and Boates being small, and thin sided, are easily swallowed by a rough Sea, not daring to adventure far in fair weather, by reason of their weakness for fear of stormes.</p>
                  <p>5. The <hi>Hollanders</hi> are industri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and no sooner are discharged of loading, but presently put forth for more, and seek for Markets abroad as well as at home; whereas our
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:40895:57"/>
                     <hi>English</hi> after they had been once at Sea, do commonly never return a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain untill all the money taken for their Fish be spent, and they in debt seeking onely to serve the next Market.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Hollanders</hi> have certain Merchants who during the Herring season do onely come to the places where the Busses arrive, and joyning together in several companies, do presently agree for the lading of 30. or 40. Busses at once, and so being discharged t<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ey may speedily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to then former Shipping; whereas our Fishermen are uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of their Chapmen, and forced to spend much time in putting off their Fish by parcells.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>What Lawes were there made to recover this trade?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>J. B.</speaker>
                  <p>It was enacted 33. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.</p>
                  <p>Because the <hi>English</hi> Fishermen dwelling on the Sea Coasts did leave off their trade of Fishing in our Seas, and went the halfe Seas over, and there upon the Seas did buy fish
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:40895:57"/> of <hi>Pickards, Flemmings, Normans, Zealanders;</hi> by reason whereof ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny incommodities did grow to the Realme, <hi>viz.</hi> The decay of the wealth and prosperity as well of the Cinque Ports, and Members of the same as of other Coast Towns by the Sea side, which were builded, and inhabited by great multitudes of people, by reason of using and exercising the craft and feat of fish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Secondly, the decay of a great number of Boates and Ships. And thirdly, the decay of many good Marriners, both able in body by their diligence, labour, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual exercise of fishing, and expert by reason thereof in the knowledge of the Sea Coasts, as well within this Realme as in other parts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas. It was therefore enacted that no manner of persons, <hi>English,</hi> Denizens, or strangers at that time, or any time after dwelling in <hi>England,</hi> should buy any Fish of any Strangers in the said Ports of <hi>Flanders, Zealand, Picardy, France,</hi>
                     <pb n="104" facs="tcp:40895:58"/> or upon the Sea between shore and shore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Act by many Continuances was continued from Parliament to Parliament untill the first of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and from thence to the end of the next Parliament and then expired.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R. V.</speaker>
                  <p>How did the <hi>Hollanders</hi> encrease in Power and Wealths?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>J. H.</speaker>
                  <p>It will be a wonderfull thing to see what a mighty subsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stence of Wealth, and a huge Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigable power that State is come to, by a rare unparalleld industry; For I dare avouch that the <hi>Roman</hi> Commonwealth, (though she had her head as well knit in her Infancy as any that ever was) did not come near her, in so short a progress of time, to such a growth of strength.</p>
                  <p>But it seemes all things conspired to raise <hi>Holland</hi> to this pass: First, the humour of the people, being patient and industrious, and of a genious more inclinable to a Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratical Government then to a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy:
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:40895:58"/> Add hereunto the quality of the Country, being every where halfe cut, and as it were inlayed with water, and thereby much for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, and made in many places in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accessible; so that if need were, <hi>Holland</hi> could turn her self into a huge pond when she list.</p>
                  <p>Hereunto concurred a further advantage of scituation, having be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind her the <hi>Baltique</hi> Sea, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords her all kind of Materials for Shipping, and for all kind of Nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Military Forces, <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> both swarming with superfluous people, suspectfull of the <hi>Spainish</hi> greatness, and so not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to contribute Auxiliary strength for mutual security and conservation.</p>
                  <p>Navigation and Mercautile Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiation, are two Poles whereon the State doth move, and to both these it seemes Nature her self hath expresly de<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>igned both Country and People; them by an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary kind of propensity, the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:40895:59"/> by apt position, for having no land to manure it, they plow the very bowels of the deep, the wrink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led forehead of <hi>Neptune</hi> being the furrowes that yields them encrease.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, there being great Rivers that slice and cut the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try up and down to disgorge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves into the Ocean, those Rivers may be said to pay them tribute, as well as to the Sea; which Rivers branching themselves into large and bearing streams, did so fitly serve one another, and all the whole, that it may be said, Nature in the frame of humane bodies did not discover more art in distributing the veines and arteries, for the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily conveyance of the mass of blood into each part, as she hath shewed here in dispersing those waters so orderly for Traffick.</p>
                  <p>These Rivers bring her what the large content of <hi>Germany,</hi> and other Eastern Countries afford, and she lying between them and the Sea, furnisheth them with all far fetched
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:40895:59"/>
                     <hi>Indian, Affrica,</hi> and <hi>Spainish</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities.</p>
                  <p>Here you shall see the most indust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious people upon earth making a rare virtue of necessity, for the same thing which makes a Parret speak, makes them to labour; For having nothing of their own, yet they bound with all things, and may be said, to live by the idleness of some of Neighbours, I am loath to name here who they are.</p>
                  <p>Here you shall find a people grow rich also by that which useth to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poverish others, even by Warrs, for prizes and booties abroad, go to make a good part of their wealth.</p>
                  <p>Yet in conversation they are but heavy, of a homely outside, and slow in action, which slowness carrieth with it a notable perseverence, and this may be imputed to the quality of that mould of earth, whereon they dwell, which may be said to be a kind of standing pool of Aire: and which is known to have such a force of assimilation, that when
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:40895:60"/> people of a more vivacious temper come to mingle with them at the second Generation, they seem to participate of the soile and aire, and degenerate into meer <hi>Hollanders;</hi> the like is found daily in Horses and Dogs, and all other Animals.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>Occulta est Batavae quaedam vis insita terrae</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>One remarkable piece of policy I forgot, that we should observe in the united Provinces, <hi>viz.</hi> Why in so small an extent of ground they have so many rich well built and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous Townes amongst them; one of the principal reasons is, because they oppropriate some staple mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Commodity to every one of the great Towns, as <hi>Amsterdam</hi> hath the Trade of the East and West-<hi>Indies, Rotterdam</hi> the <hi>English</hi> Cloth, <hi>Dort</hi> the Rhenish Wines, <hi>Trevers</hi> the <hi>Se<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ts</hi> Trade, the <hi>Hague</hi> the Resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Prince, and the States, <hi>Haerlam</hi> subsists by Knitting and Dying, &amp;c. which is a very laudable course, not to suffer one place to
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:40895:60"/> swallow the wealth and traffick of the whole; like the spleen in the natural body, whose swelling makes all the rest of the Members languish.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray what is their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>O. F.</speaker>
                  <p>Their Excise is an unwasted Mine, which with the infiniteness of their Traffick, and their unwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried industry is paid them by every part of the World, the Sea yields them by two sorts of Fishes onely Herrins and Cod 60000l. a year, for which they go out sometimes 7. or 8000. Boates at once, and are able to set out twice as many Ships: their Merchandize amounting forty years ago to a million, whereas <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> which is twice as big in compass hath not half so much.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>How do they amass so much Treasure?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>O. F.</speaker>
                  <p>Whether it be from the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of their Country, where they must work or perish; or their geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us adapted to such a situation, or their own parcimonious inclination
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:40895:61"/> and education; or their transcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Activity or close habitation that compact and fortifie their vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues they are young and old; man and woman (for all souls are there Masculine,) the most industrious and deligent people on earth, and in their several wayes contribute to the publick Treasury.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>How do they raise and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose of their Revenue?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C. B.</speaker>
                  <p>They raise one year with the other for the common charge of the Union, (besides the extraordinary Impositions that rise and fall with their occasions) 3200000. Crownes, <hi>i. e.</hi> 800000. upon the particular Provinces, <hi>Holland</hi> contributing half, <hi>Zealand</hi> a fifth part, and <hi>Friezland</hi> about a tenth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>Their charge is great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering the small Circuit of their Ground?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C. B.</speaker>
                  <p>1. Their Traffick makes good what is wanting in their Land, the commodiousness for the Sea, the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:40895:61"/> narrowness of their ground, and the industry of the Inhabitants, the defects of nature.</p>
                  <p>2. But the people bear it pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently because their liberty could not long endure without Armes, nor Armes without stipends, nor their stipends without impositions, and the united Provinces will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies so apprehend the Power of <hi>Spain,</hi> or their other enemies, as they will easily be perswaded, to be alwaies prepared for Warr that so they may the easier evade all new hazards.</p>
                  <p>3. They put forty dayes in the Souldiers moneth for pay, and so save a great deal of money, and pay exactly which prevents a great deal of disorder incident to more needy Armies.</p>
                  <p>4. They raise the money to maintain the Banks and Channels of each Province, and out of their Treasuries advance a publick Stock.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>But a word Sir of their strength by Sea?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:40895:62"/>
                  <speaker>C. B.</speaker>
                  <p>As they equal all <hi>Europe</hi> in Trade, so they exceed it in the number of their Ships; which people as it were the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Seas, especially before <hi>Amsterdam</hi> that hath engrossed the Western trade of <hi>Antwerp,</hi> and that Eastern of <hi>Lisbon;</hi> and is the staple as <hi>Rotterdam</hi> is the Arsenal of that Country which is entrenched with the Sea, and <hi>Bull</hi> worked with Ships: they have no Timber growing, yet they sell Timber to most Nations, besides what they use themselves: they are dull by Land, but water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devils at Sea, being all Seamen born, and bred either in Merchandizing, or Sea-faring, and like Frogs can live both of Land and Water; not a Country <hi>Ʋriester</hi> or Waterman but can handle an Oare, steer a Boat, raise a Mast, and bear you out in the roughest streights you come at; Sailers among them are as common as Beggers among us: they can drink, raile, swear, nigle, streat and be lowsy alike; but a mess of
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:40895:62"/> their Knaves is worth a million of ours, for they in a boisterous rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness can work, live and toile; <q>Whereas ours will rather laze themselves to poverty, and like Cabbages left out in Winter rot away in the loathsomeless of a nauseous sloath; in Fleets they can fight close and rather hazard all then save some while others perish, but single they will slag and fear like Birds in a Bush, when the Sparrow-hawks bills are heard.</q> Their Fisher Boates pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them for the Ships, and fishing fits them for fighting.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>No doubt but <hi>Amsterdam, Middleburgh,</hi> &amp;c. are full of Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, because so full of trade in Merchandizing, or shipping, but how do they furnish themselves with Necessaries?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C. B.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Holland</hi> hath no Corn yet plentifull granaries; no hemp or Flax, yet store of Cordage and Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen; no Wool or Cattel, yet abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Cloath and Provision of all
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:40895:63"/> sorts, not a stick of Wood, yet more Ships then all <hi>Europe</hi> besides.</p>
                  <p>But that which compleats their strength and power at Sea is their skill in Navigation, not a Climate Star or wind but they understand, not a Sea but their youth are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to, nor a streight or passage but they are shewed: so that they can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gross the <hi>Indies, Basile,</hi> the <hi>Portugal,</hi> cousen the <hi>Spaniard</hi> abuse the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish,</hi> and carry all at Sea before them; <q>Onely a <hi>Turkish</hi> man of Warr is as dreadful to them as a Falcon to a Mallord, against whom their best remedies is to steal a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>L. M.</speaker>
                  <p>But there is a Gentleman that can give you the exactest ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of any man concerning that Countrey, having been seven years Leiger there. Sir, I pray, you can tell what makes that State so pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperous.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>T. O.</speaker>
                  <p>All things concurred for the rising and maintaining of this State, the disposition of the people
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:40895:63"/> being, as mutinous, so industrious and frugall; The nature of the Country every where fortifiable with water; the scituation of it having behind them the Baltique Sea, which yields them all materials for ships, and many other commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>L. M.</speaker>
                  <p>Good Sir, the manner of their Government?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>T. O.</speaker>
                  <p>For the manner of their Government, they have upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion an Assembly of the General States, like our Parliament, being composed of those which are sent from every Province upon sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and what these enact, stands for Law; then is there besides a Councel of State, residing for the most part at the <hi>Hague,</hi> which at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend daily occasions, being rather imployed upon Affairs of <hi>State,</hi> than of particular Justice. The most po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in this Counsel was <hi>Barnavil,</hi> by reason of his Advocates in <hi>Holland,</hi> and besides both these, every Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince and great Town have particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:40895:64"/> Counsels of their own, to all which Assemblies, as well of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral States, as the rest, the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try is called for order sake; But the State indeed is <hi>Democratical,</hi> the Merchant and the Tradesman being predominant, the Gentlemen now but few and poor, and even at the beginning the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> saw it safer to rely upon the Towns than them, Neither are the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try so much ingaged in the cause, the people having more advantage in a Free State, than in a Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy.</p>
                  <p>Their care in Government is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry exact and particular, by reason that every one hath an immediate interest in the State, such is the equality of Justice, that it renders every man satisfied, such the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Regularity, as a man may see their Laws were made to Guide, not to Entrap, such their Exactness in casting the expence of an Army, as that it shall be equally far from superfluity and want, and as much
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:40895:64"/> order and certainty in their acts of War, as in ours of Peace, teaching it to be both Civil and Rich, and they still retain that sign of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth yet uncorrupted, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Poverty, and publick Wealth, for no one private man there is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Rich, and few very Poor, and no State more sumptuous in all publick things.</p>
                  <p>But the question is, whether this being a Free State will as well sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist in Peace, as it hath done hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to in War, Peace leaving every one to attend his particular Wealth, when Fear while the War lasts, makes them concur for their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon safety, and <hi>Zealand</hi> upon the least security, hath been ever envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous at the predominancy of <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>Ʋtrecht</hi> ready to mutiny for Religion; and besides, it is a doubt whether the same care and sincerity would continue if they were at their consistence, as appears yet whilst they are but in rising.</p>
                  <p>The Revenue of this State ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:40895:65"/> chiefly from the Earl of <hi>Hollands</hi> Demesnes, the confiscated Church Livings, the rising and falling of money, which they use with much advantage, their Fishing upon our Coasts, and those of <hi>Norway,</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution out of the enemies Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, Taxes upon all things at home, and Imposition upon all Merchandizes ftom abroad; their expences upon their Ambassadors, their shipping, their ditches, their rampiers and munition, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly they have in pay by Sea and Land 60000 men.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>L. M.</speaker>
                  <p>If it be not too trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some to you, a word or two of their Strength, Discipline &amp; War.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>T. O.</speaker>
                  <p>For their Strength, the nature of the Countrey makes them able to defend themselves long by Land; neither could any thing have indangered them so much as the last great frost, had not the Treaty been then on foot, because the Enemy being then Master of the field, that renders their Ditches, Marshes, and
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:40895:65"/> Rivers, as firm Ground, and by Sea they are able to offend any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p>There belong to the State 2000 Vessels of all sorts, so that if the <hi>Spaniard</hi> were entirely beaten out of those parts, the King of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France</hi> would take as much pains to suppress, as ever they did to raise them; for being our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, they are able to give us the Law at <hi>Sea,</hi> and eat us out of all Trade, much more the <hi>French,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving at this time three ships for our one, though none so good as our best.</p>
                  <p>Now that whereupon the most part of their Revenue and Strength depends is their Traffick, in which mistery of State they are at this day the wisest, for all the Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities which this part of the World wants and the <hi>Indies</hi> have, is Spice, Silk, Jewels, Gold, they are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Conveyors of them to the rest of Christendom except us; as the <hi>Venitians</hi> were of old, and all
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:40895:66"/> those Commodities that these Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Countreys abound with, and those Southern stand in need of, they likewise convey thither, which was the ancient Trade of the Easter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings; And this they do, having little to export of their own, by buying of their Neighbour Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys the former, and selling them again what they bring back at their own prises, and so consequently live upon the idleness of others; And to this purpose their scituation serves fitly, for the River of the <hi>Rhene,</hi> the <hi>Maze,</hi> and <hi>Skeld</hi> end all in their Dominions, and the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique Sea lyes not far from them, all which affords them whatever the great Continent of <hi>Germany, Russia</hi> and <hi>Poland</hi> yields; then they again lying between <hi>Germany</hi> and the Sea, do furnish it back with all Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities foreign.</p>
                  <p>To remember some pieces of their Discipline, as patterns of the rest, The Watches at Night are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all of one Nation, so that they
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:40895:66"/> can hardly concur to give up any one Town.</p>
                  <p>The Commissaries are no where so strict upon Musters, and where he finds a company, thither he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth them, so that when an Army marcheth, the List and the Poll are never far disagreeing.</p>
                  <p>Their Army is ever well Cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, well Armed, and had never yet occasion to mutiny for Pay or Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als.</p>
                  <p>The Souldiers commit no where fewer Insolencies upon the Burgers, fewer Robberies upon the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, nor the Officers fewer Deceits upon the Souldiers.</p>
                  <p>And lastly, they provide well that their General shall have small means to invade their Liberties; For first, their Army is composed of many Nations, which have their several Commanders, and the Commanders are disposed by the States them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, not by the General; And secondly, he hath never an implicite Commission left to Discretion, but
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:40895:67"/> by reason their Countrey hath no great bounds, receives daily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands what to do.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>L. M.</speaker>
                  <p>Your Judgement of the place and people.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>T. O.</speaker>
                  <p>The Territory containes six entire Provinces, <hi>Holland, Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Ʋtrecht, Groninghen, Over-Yssel,</hi> and <hi>Friezland,</hi> and certain Towns in <hi>Brabant</hi> and <hi>Flanders,</hi> the ground of which is for the most part fruitful, the Towns no where so equally Beautiful, Rich and Strong, which equality grows by reason that they appropriate some one Staple Commoditie to every Town of note; onely <hi>Amsterdam</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly passeth them all, but even <hi>Sevil, Lisbon,</hi> or any other Mart Town in Christendome; and to it is appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated the Trade of the <hi>East Indies,</hi> where they maintain commonly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ships, besides which, there go twice a year from it, and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning Towns, a great Fleet to the Baltique Sea; upon the fall of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twerp</hi> that rose rather than <hi>Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough,</hi>
                     <pb n="123" facs="tcp:40895:67"/> though it stand at the same Rivers mouth, and is their second Mart Town, to which is appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted our <hi>English</hi> Cloth.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the People, they are neither much Devout, nor much Wicked, given all to Drink, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minently to no other Vice; hard in bargaining, but just; surly and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spectless, as in all Democracies; thrifty, industrious, and cleanly, dishartened upon the least ill suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess, and insolent upon good; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventive in manufactures, cunning in Traffick, and generally for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Action; that natural slow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of theirs suits better by reason of the advisedness and perseverance it brings with it, than the rashness and changeableness of the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Florentine</hi> Wits; and the equallity of spirits which is among them and the <hi>Switzers,</hi> renders them so fit for a Democracie, which kind of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, Nations of more subtile Wits being once come to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistent greatness have seldome long endured.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:40895:68"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>The Lives and Characters of the Princes of Aurange.</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>THe Affaires of <hi>Holland</hi> depending so much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Princes of <hi>Aurange,</hi> will you be pleased to recollect the History of those renowned Princes?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>T. S.</speaker>
                  <p>1475. <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>Chalon</hi> was invested by King <hi>Lewis</hi> with the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute Principality of <hi>Aurange,</hi> which is on the Northwest of <hi>Province,</hi> and subject to the King of <hi>France.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>1480. He dieth and leaveth his Estate and Government to his vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant and active Successor <hi>William Chalon,</hi> whose Interest abroad and Prowess at home, was so consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that <hi>Lewis</hi> the 11. could not think himself secure, untill he had submitted his Estate to him in the Parliament of <hi>Daulphin,</hi> and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried his Cozen, upon which submis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion and alliance he receives his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:40895:68"/> again in <hi>Capite</hi> from his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign,</p>
                  <p>Which being much improved, he bequeathed to <hi>John Chalon;</hi> who was able to justifie the King of <hi>France</hi> his Jealousie, and make himself so considerable that <hi>France</hi> feared him, when an enemy, the Duke of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> courted him for a friend, in whose service he died; And,</p>
                  <p>1496. Left his Patrimony and authority to <hi>Philibert Chalon</hi> his Nephew who was Heir to his Reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions as well as to his Estate, and died as faithful a servant to the House of <hi>Austria</hi> under <hi>Charles,</hi> as he to the House of <hi>Burgundy</hi> under <hi>Philip</hi> the Good: These Princes were born to assist afflicted States, to relieve oppressed Princes, to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port tottering Crownes, and rescue lost Liberties; especially if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider how the <hi>Chalon</hi> male Line failed in <hi>Philibert,</hi> and the honour of <hi>Nassaw</hi> was wreathen with the glory of <hi>Aurange.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:40895:69"/>
                  <p> 1500. For <hi>Philibert</hi> onely Sister being <hi>Married</hi> to <hi>Rene Nassau</hi> as he himself was devoted to him, <hi>Renes</hi> Son <hi>Henry Nassau</hi> is adopted by <hi>Philibert,</hi> who failing of an Heir of his body, would have one of his Virtues; and as Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> said that her Throne was the Throne of Kings; so he ordered that his Principalities should be the inheritances of Nobles.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> was born a Prince and bred a Souldier, his blood enobling his Name and his actions his blood; the brave man being resolved first to deserve, and then to inherit his Dominions; he as nobly served the King of <hi>Spain</hi> to chastise his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects Rebellion as his Successors did the people to oppose his Tiranny; he fought but against licentiousness, and they but for liberty; he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowed his own Revenue in his Masters service, and his Masters sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary in his Souldiers encouragement carrying nothing out of the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands but the glory of Conquest
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:40895:69"/> and Integrity: Having taught <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Flanders</hi> six things, 1. how to Intrench and Fortifie double; 2. how to retreat safely; 3. how to embatle the Foot; 4. Deep se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely; 5. how to bear a charge undauntingly and return it home; 6. how to tire an Army with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied surprizes; and 7. how to conquer with kindness. He died before <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> falling the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expressible joy of his enemies, and unuterable sorrow of his friends; but that,</p>
                  <p>1544. His Cosen <hi>William</hi> suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded him in his Estate and Glory, his Heir by his Will and his Peoples Vote, whose expectation of this Prince was no less then his merit which promised much and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med more: Born he was at <hi>Dellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> and bred in <hi>Germany</hi> with Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> who learned in one School what they might practise in contrary Camps; honourable was his possession in <hi>France,</hi> noble in <hi>Germany,</hi> but large and rich in the
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:40895:70"/> Low Countries; whose Religion now reformed, provoked the Pope, as their Privileges now enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged vexed <hi>Charles</hi> the Emperour into some close Overtures, as it did his Son <hi>Philip</hi> to open attempts upon them; an inquisition is set up, impositions are enhanced, strangers (as <hi>de Sylon, de Feria</hi>) &amp; Tirants (as D'<hi>Alva</hi> and <hi>Granvill</hi>) are set over them; Goods are confifcated, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states seized, Freemen outlawed, and a multitude of honest Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants are put to death; the people groan under this, and fear worse; much troubled were the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, more the Nobility, whereof among many that were eminent for birth, valour, and adherency, two were most considerable, 1. <hi>Lamorall,</hi> Count <hi>Egmont</hi> a Souldier, and <hi>William</hi> Prince of <hi>Aurange</hi> a States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, the one trusted with the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est commands, the other famous for most eminent services, first at St. <hi>Quintin,</hi> and then at <hi>Graveling;</hi> the Prince of <hi>Aurange</hi> was popular,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:40895:70"/> wary, wise, a great master of speech, and no less of Councel; his carriage and behaviour plausible; of whom it was a question whether he was more able in comprehending busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness or morewary in managing them: <hi>Egmont</hi> was rather a man of Warr then peace, one of a candid nature and obliging; converse and popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar too, but among the Souldiers in the fields rather then among the vulgar within the Walls, fitter for the preferments of Campe then Court: The Prince of <hi>Aurange</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding while he was Hostage for King <hi>Philip</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> that those two Princes designed the extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Protestant Religion, communicates the Plot to the <hi>Fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish</hi> Nobility in a seasonable juncture, when they were impover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ished by the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> when present with them, slighted by the continual absence of <hi>Philip,</hi> and awed by the surintendency of strangers; when the Churchmen were unsatisfied with new erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:40895:71"/> Bishoprickes upon the ruines of Monasteries; when all were amazed to see <hi>Germans</hi> and <hi>Spaniards</hi> brought into their Counsels, Forts, and Garrisons; when <hi>France</hi> was divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in its self under young <hi>Francis; England</hi> reformed by Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> and the Protestant Princes threatned by the greatness of <hi>Austria</hi> watched all opportunities to diminish it.</p>
                  <p>King <hi>Philip</hi> finding his Dominions large but unsetled, retires to the middest of them, as the heart to dispense vigour and influence to all the Party; and (waving the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chess of <hi>Lorrain</hi> whom the Prince and the States desired) setled <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet</hi> of <hi>Parma,</hi> with Cardinal <hi>Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill</hi> in the Government; but before his departure he might see discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in the faces, and discern rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion in the <hi>Harangues,</hi> of the Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties he called together at <hi>Gaunt,</hi> and if he saw it not, his Courtiers did upon a good token that when one of them urged to him the danger of
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:40895:71"/> these Provinces if he moderated not his Edicts concerning Religion, he answered, <hi>That he would rather be without Kingdomes then enjoy them with Heresy:</hi> dangerous it was to refuse these <hi>Dutchmen</hi> least those Provinces might revolt, more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to endulge them least all his Dominions would set up liberty, the Edicts are confirmed; the old constitution is established; a juncto is privately marked out, the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chess is instructed, and the King is bound for <hi>Spain,</hi> when the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verness and her Cardinal find griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances swelling up the publick dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content, and improve them by their <hi>juncto cabals,</hi> their absolute autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and arbitrary Government, especially <hi>Granvills</hi> imperiousnes, who was a man of great experience, and of greater animosity; for hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on grave <hi>William,</hi> the Prince, <hi>Horne</hi> the Admiral, and valient <hi>Egmont</hi> the Souldier suggested first more pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately to the Nobility how their Counsels were excluded, and then
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:40895:72"/> more publickly to the people, how their Privileges were endangered, adding to the Governess her self, (who in strait between the strict injunctions of <hi>Spain,</hi> and the bitter complaints of the people, had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther refuge but her promises) that an Assembly of Estates was the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remedy, a motion ill resented in its self, the ill humours of that Country being never likely to do well in a general Assembly, where they might rather confederate then break, and worse, as proceeding from <hi>Aurange,</hi> whom <hi>Granvill</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presents as crafty and ambitious, occasioning a stricter execution of the Edicts untill authority is bafled, liberty declared; Libells are pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished and under the notion of commerce the Protestant Religion is every day improved, liberty of Conscience is challenged, and the Privileges of their Country are pleaded for; the Prince of <hi>Aurange</hi> first had correspondence and then made alliance with the Admiral,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:40895:72"/> the Governour gives way to the new Alterations; the Cardinal rageth, the Nobility agree upon one Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which was a course to unite themselves, and deride the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, against whom they drew so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny complaints, contrived so many designs, by disowning and disparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him and his Confederates, that the King allaying the vigor of his former resolutions, according to the temper of the people, recalled <hi>Granvil,</hi> to the present satisfaction of all <hi>Flanders;</hi> but <hi>Viglio</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemont</hi> going their way, &amp; the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Trents</hi> Decrees being publish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Prince of <hi>Aurange</hi> now alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the most eminent <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans,</hi> proposed, that matters of Government and Religion might be transacted in the Council of State, which the Dutchess oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, as prejudicial to his Majesty and her self, the Council is divided, the execution of the Edicts is stop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped; the Protestants increase; Count <hi>Egmont</hi> is sent to <hi>Spain,</hi> with
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:40895:73"/> instructions from him, to discover the bottom of their disorders; the King is resolved; the Dutchess calls a Conference of Bishops, Divines, and Lawyers, at <hi>Brussels;</hi> the Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition is brought in; their sense of what they suffered, and the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hensions of what they feared, forced the people to a Confederacy, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived by <hi>Philip Mornishies</hi> Lord of St. <hi>Aldegond;</hi> a Covenant is taken, and published, all sorts are engaged; the design is applauded, fears and jealousies are increased; the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> and the other Nobility debate matters at <hi>Breda,</hi> under the notion of a marriage; they assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at <hi>Brussels,</hi> present their suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, aggravate the grievances, (particularly <hi>Brederode</hi> a Noble per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, of an active spirit and a voluble tongue, at Count <hi>Collemberghs</hi> house, <hi>April</hi> 3. 1566.) with great applause: they go in order to the Regent, and Petition, appealing to God and Men, that they had done what lay in their power: and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:40895:73"/> occasion from the word <hi>Gueux,</hi> or Beggars, as they were called by <hi>Barlemont,</hi> they cried out, Long live the King, long live the <hi>Gueux,</hi> and by this Bread, by this Salt, by this Budget, the <hi>Gueux</hi> will from their tenets never budge; yea, the Medal at their Girdles is, true to the King, even to the Budget.</p>
                  <p>The Liberty of other Nations is Printed, Protestant Sermons are publickly Preached, the Edict is se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely injoyned, the people flock after the Novelties, and arm them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves against the Law, the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of the Provinces draw off from the Dutches; the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> now things are <hi>ripe,</hi> distracts the Counsel and the King in <hi>Spain;</hi> summons the Estates privately to <hi>Getrinberge</hi> in <hi>Liege;</hi> they resolve to stand to their Liberty; they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that nothing was to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from <hi>Spain</hi> but delays; they demolish Idolatrous Monuments, defaced the Churches, affronted the Priests, and being rather inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:40895:74"/> than moderated by the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> his expedients, his water a flame: the Tumult began by few, was desired by many, and approved by all; all the Calvinisme of <hi>Europe</hi> was in <hi>Antwerp,</hi> and all <hi>Antwerp</hi> was engaged at first, and by their exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple all the Provinces, so that the Dutchess is with much ado perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by <hi>Orange</hi> and <hi>Egmont</hi> to stay at <hi>Brussels</hi> to countenance their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings.</p>
                  <p>The Discontented were so nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous, that they were <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reated with, and yielded to, in point of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence and Liberty, each grant weakening authority, and strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ening the tumult; which <hi>Orange,</hi> under pretence of appeasing, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved; the Regent is in arms, the Confederates consult, <hi>Antwerp</hi> is reduced, and the whole Country inclined to Peace: the Reformers are discounteranced in <hi>Spain,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> for eseeing it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible to please the King and serve his Country, in those troublesome
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:40895:74"/> times, would have retired, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing disswaded by the Regent, he and his brother <hi>Lodowick</hi> comply with the present humors, keep their Protestant correspondencies in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> meet with other Nobility at <hi>Terramode</hi> in <hi>Brabant,</hi> near <hi>Antwerp;</hi> Count <hi>William</hi> discovering and opening the <hi>Spanish</hi> design, incited to Arms; <hi>Egmont</hi> reflecting on the weakness and poverty of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, his own services and great Family, and the power of <hi>Spain,</hi> was inclined to the peace and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity of his Countrey, in which temper the Assembly broke up, <hi>Egmont</hi> being really, and <hi>Orange</hi> feignedly for Peace.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>How began the War?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C. B.</speaker>
                  <p>By the Dutchess her reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution in order to the execution of her Edicts to ingarrison <hi>Valentiennes</hi> and <hi>Antwerp,</hi> both which places, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter much debate among the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, opposed it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D. L.</speaker>
                  <p>What thought they of this in <hi>Spain?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:40895:75"/>
                  <speaker>C. B.</speaker>
                  <p>Count <hi>Ferza</hi> was for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence that might break, rather than for force that would unite them; <hi>Alva</hi> is for Authority that should give Law to <hi>Flanders,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than Clemency, that received Laws from them; and for an Army rather than an Amnesty; whose ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, seconded with <hi>Granviles,</hi> and the news from <hi>Flanders,</hi> fixed the unresolved King upon a great Army under <hi>Alva,</hi> a souldier from his cradle, very rigid in Aspect, more in Nature, haughty in Peace, more in War; he musters at <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain</hi> 12000 foot and 3000 horse, and marcheth without interruption to <hi>Lucemberg,</hi> w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> he ingarrisoned; the Country amazed to hear of, more to see his Forces, and ready to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, <hi>Orange</hi> and his brother flyeth, <hi>Egmmt</hi> and <hi>Horn</hi> are privately secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in <hi>Flanders, Montigns</hi> and <hi>Berg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her</hi> in <hi>Spain:</hi> and their Secretaries that could discover all transactions he wracked; the Dutchess remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved her self: he sets up a new Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:40895:75"/> of Justice, cites the Nobility before him, upon pain of being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed Traitors; the Markets run with bloud, for his Executions were publick; the Countrey was but one great prison, kept in by his new forts and cittadels; the Nobility fly to <hi>Aurange,</hi> and the people to <hi>England,</hi> some decline his Juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction by appealing to the King, others who had estates in <hi>Germany,</hi> to the Emperour; <hi>Breda</hi> the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s chief Town he secured; his eldest Son, a youth at <hi>Lovain,</hi> he took, his goods were confiscated; Despair arms the Confederates, and and pitty and interest from <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> now engaged with <hi>Spain,</hi> as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sists them; and it was but appearing in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and the harrazed Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey would flock in to them: the Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> and the <hi>Hans</hi> Towns assist them, both out of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest and Conscience, equally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the house of <hi>Austria</hi> and the Pope: a Diet is kept; the slow pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedures of it are quenched by the
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:40895:76"/> Active Prince, imprinting that Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor on other breasts that enflamed his own; the <hi>English</hi> were to enter <hi>Friezeland,</hi> the <hi>Germans Brabant,</hi> the <hi>Hugonits</hi> the <hi>Walloon</hi> side: disbanded souldiers are entertained; Prince <hi>Lodowick</hi> entereth <hi>Frieze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Lumay</hi> and <hi>Villiers</hi> surprize <hi>Gelderland,</hi> but are prevented at <hi>Ruremond,</hi> and pursued, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing <hi>Londonios</hi> Advise, not to provoke too many enemies, as far as <hi>Liege,</hi> where they are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown; no better success have they at <hi>Graves,</hi> a convenient place for their purpose, and at <hi>Brussels</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Dukes person. But <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowick</hi> had 10000 foot, 3000 horse, and the Prince as many more. But one <hi>Balthazar Gerard,</hi> set on by the Jesuits, and recommended to his Highness by Monsieur <hi>du Pre,</hi> my Lord <hi>Mansfield,</hi> under pretence of being a Martyrs son, and offering some useful Blanks he had got from the enemy, got himself first to his Chamber, and then to his Bosome,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:40895:76"/> untill he had shot him as he came from Dinner; so that he said no more but, my God! take pitty of my soul, and this poor people. A most Wise, Constant, Magnanimous, Patient, and Excellent Prince, his Motto being <hi>Mediis tranquillus in undis.</hi>—</p>
                  <p>Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> succeeded him at 17 year old, with this Inscription, <hi>tandem fit surculus arbor,</hi> his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct and the Earl of <hi>Leicester,</hi> in the general Government of the Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, where after many incursions into the enemies Countrey, the taking of <hi>Breda,</hi> that was bestowed on the Prince, the relief of <hi>Nordan,</hi> the reduction of <hi>Steenberguen,</hi> the siege of <hi>Zutphen,</hi> the subduing of <hi>Groeninguen,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Parma's</hi> defeat in the <hi>Betuwe,</hi> the settlement of the Eastern and Western trade, the great Victory on the plain cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Tresche-Heyde;</hi> he brought the <hi>Spaniard</hi> to a Peace, the <hi>English</hi> to a League, and his own people to a peaceable submission to his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:40895:77"/> and so died full of Honour and Dayes; leaving the Principality to Count <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Nassaw</hi> that great States-man, that designed an Alliance with all <hi>Europe,</hi> and a Marriage with <hi>England,</hi> whose Daughter he honoured as his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess, rather than his Daughter in Law: he dying when his designs were most ripe, for settlement with <hi>Barnevell,</hi> and <hi>Grotius</hi> his assistance, left his son Prince <hi>William</hi> heir to his power and design, but not to his success, for his enterprize on <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterdam</hi> failed a little before he died; and left his hopefull son <hi>William</hi> that now Governs, whom <hi>Holland</hi> is jealous of, and uncivil to, but all the rest of the Provinces and people honour, according to his own, and his great Ancestors merit and ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; whom universal love and vote, his Predecessors service, his Countreys interest, his own emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence and his Allies power, will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance to no less grandeur and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than any of his Renowned Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:40895:77"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Concerning our last Wars, and other transactions with the</hi> Dutch, <hi>from</hi> 1612. <hi>to</hi> 1660.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. <hi>M.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>HOw have we agreed with the <hi>Hollanders</hi> since they were a Free State?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R. B.</speaker>
                  <p>Pretty well, only we clash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed sometimes about the <hi>East-Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Trade, and the Fishing upon the Narrow Seas.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. <hi>M.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>What clashing had we with them about the Trade beyond the Line?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R. B.</speaker>
                  <p>They, not contented with the ordinary course of a fair Trade, took divers Islands, built several Forts, and endeavoured a new Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over us, and those <hi>Moluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos, Banda, Amboyna, &amp;c.</hi> exercising new Jurisdictions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. <hi>M.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>How were these differences put up?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="144" facs="tcp:40895:78"/>
                  <speaker>R. B.</speaker>
                  <p>It was like to be a breach, but in the year 1613. the States sent their Ambassadours with full power to offer any satisfaction, and when that succeeded not, in the year 1615. they offered more in a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty at the <hi>Hague,</hi> touching the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences between the <hi>English</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> in the <hi>East-Indies;</hi> and at last in a third Treaty at <hi>London,</hi> in the year 1619. there was a full and solemn composition made of all the said differences, and a fair or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der set for the future proceeding in both Companies, as well in the course of their Trade and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, as otherwise.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. M.</speaker>
                  <p>What was the next breach?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R. B.</speaker>
                  <p>That at <hi>Amboyna,</hi> which King <hi>James</hi> had not time, nor King <hi>Charles</hi> opportunity or power to require satisfaction, for his Subjects in <hi>England</hi> being as insolent in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying him assistance, as his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies were in offering him affronts, as if they had both combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:40895:78"/> and <hi>Ingratitude</hi> abroad had gone hand in hand with treason at home; for one <hi>Turner</hi> said that we had better die by a forreign ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my then submit to home slavery.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>F. M.</speaker>
                  <p>But did that excellent Prince of famous memory agree with them all his reign?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R. B.</speaker>
                  <p>The <hi>Hollanders</hi> and others encroaching upon the Fishers and other our Rights in the Narrow Seas, yea things coming to that pass by their observation of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toward humour of the <hi>English</hi> at home, that they disputed our Right by <hi>Grotius;</hi> his Sacred Majesty thought fit not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to employ Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> to <hi>cleare</hi> the Right; but the Earle of <hi>Lindsey</hi> as Admiral, and the Earle of <hi>Essex</hi> as Vice-Admiral, with 40. Saile set out with the Shipmoney to secure it; whereby the <hi>English</hi> puissance was rendered so considerable, and trade so safe in the eyes of forreign Princes, that the King of <hi>Spain</hi> thought it his safest course to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trust
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:40895:79"/> his Bullion in our Bottoms, which was coined in <hi>England,</hi> to the great benefit of the Kings Mint, and of all the Merchants also, whose Commodities were exchanged thereby, and the rest of the money paid over by exchange to <hi>Flanders;</hi> whereupon the <hi>Hollander</hi> courted his Majesty with Presents, 1. of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergrease, 2. transparent China Basons, 3. a Clock, and 4. the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals of <hi>Tintoret</hi> and <hi>Titian.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And in the year 1636. the King considering the good effects of his late Fleet, sets out another con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisting of 60. Saile of good Ships un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Earle of <hi>Northumberlands</hi> Command, who going Northwards scoured the Seas of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Busses, seizing some, sinking others, and enforcing the rest to fly; so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing them all to a precarious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of entreating the favour of Fishing by the Kings Commission, which he was the readier to indulge them, because he looked upon them as the most likely instruments for his
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:40895:79"/> Nephews Restauration to the Palatinate.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>L. M.</speaker>
                  <p>But was there not some difference about the <hi>Dutch</hi> Fight with the <hi>Spanish</hi> Admiral upon our Coast?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R. B.</speaker>
                  <p>Our Historians say that our reputation was hereby greatly <note place="margin">Sir <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard Baker</hi> continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> impaired for suffering the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> to fall upon the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in our Seas; and they say likewise that they doubting that we might resent the affront done us in that action, were willing to keep us so busied that we should have no opportunity of retaliation and to that end they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated the <hi>Scots,</hi> they say, with all manner of warlike provisions.</p>
                  <p>But that excellent Prince, then whom many might make greater shewes, none had greater affections for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, minding as well the common interest of Protestants abroad as that more particular of <hi>Englishmen</hi> at home, made a strict alliance with that state by the Marriage of his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:40895:80"/> yet when our neighbour <hi>Dutch-men</hi> minded their interest, and were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most Masters at Sea in the Northern Fishing, which because so far, and of so small a return, they went away with the whole benefit; upon our Fishmongers complaint he encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged several overtures and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects concerning Busses for our own Coasts service, the prevention of strangers, and the improvement of the Narrow Seas, and withal he broke the confederacy that was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into between the <hi>Hollanders</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> before <hi>Dunkirke.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>L. M.</speaker>
                  <p>But what did they during the Warrs in <hi>England?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R. B.</speaker>
                  <p>They sent Embassadours to the Parliament to declare that the high and mighty States of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Provinces had sent them to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate a reconciliation, that they might concurr together for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation of Popery, and the set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Protestant Religion.</p>
                  <p>Here they remained (saith Mr. <hi>Sanderson</hi> how truly I know not,)
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:40895:80"/> pretending a peace, but in earnest to settle trade, and see which way the game went, and as he adds, the King knew their minds; and then they urged very hard for the King, whom they had saved, had their Embassadour (as the same Author hath it) been as true to his trust as <hi>They</hi> were to the King.</p>
                  <p>After the Kings Death they broke with the <hi>English,</hi> and when <hi>Oliver St. John</hi> and <hi>Walter Strickland</hi> were sent into <hi>Holland</hi> they were affron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ill used by the common people, and thereupon return in discontent: Hereupon forsooth a new Act is made for the encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Shipping</hi> and <hi>Navigation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which the <hi>Hollanders</hi> apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding highly prejudicial to their trade, they laboured with all their might what by fair Messages, and what with threats to get repealed, but when they saw all their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours were in vain, they were dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to meditate hostility; <hi>Dorislaus</hi> is Executed there; the
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:40895:81"/> Kings Interest was hopefull in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Auranges</hi> therefore prevalent there; the Lord <hi>Newport</hi> comes over to feel the pulse and look into the strength, preparations and temper of the <hi>English;</hi> here the old duty of Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring-Fissing was demanded, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening of the Scheld Custome free from <hi>Middleburgh</hi> to <hi>Antwerp</hi> is ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, the right of the Flagge is insisted on, the business of <hi>Amboyna</hi> revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and their Ships in several pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces upon the foresaid act taken. As an Omen of the Warr, the Statehouse at <hi>Amsterdam</hi> is burned, a Sea Fight is seen at the mouth of the <hi>Maes;</hi> they resolve to try our pulses, and 150. Saile are equipped under <hi>Trump,</hi> while we had but 25. Saile in the <hi>Downs</hi> under <hi>Blake;</hi> they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse to strike saile upon Captain <hi>Youngs</hi> demand till he had given them some Broadsides; they set on <hi>Blake</hi> and beat him, yet not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out loss, in so much as the States excused the action, and though in
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:40895:81"/> vain renewed the Treaty, declaring before the searcher of hearts (they are their own words) <q>That they were so far from owning the late-engagement that they were asto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished at the fatal newes of it, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treating a peace upon the pledges of their Religion, and liberty;</q> signed <hi>J. Cates, G. Schaes, P. Vau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derperre;</hi> We replying our Civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to them, and their great prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations for Warr; Notwithstanding these pretences for peace voted pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent satisfaction for the charges we had been at, and security for the time to come; it comes to a Warr, they get in between S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                     <hi>George Askew</hi> who was abroad, &amp; our Navy which was going out at home, <hi>Trump</hi> se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures their Merchants, <hi>draweth</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Blake</hi> that had spoiled their Herring Busses, and tolled them for the tenth; the Freeboates are bui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie on both sides, <hi>George Askew</hi> and they engage in a drawn battle, he is thereupon discharged; the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> espouse the Kings quarrel to
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:40895:82"/> strengthen their own; the Prince of <hi>Aurange</hi> is <hi>Stad-holder,</hi> or chief Governour; St. <hi>Johns</hi> gives the States these parting words, <hi>My Lords you have an eye upon the event of Affaires in</hi> Scotland, <hi>and therefore refuse the friendship we offer; that business will be over and you will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent.</hi> Accordingly they sent more Embassadours, and more submissive termes when his Majesty was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown; <hi>De wit</hi> and <hi>Ruiter</hi> joine. they brave and dare <hi>Ayscue,</hi> but are drawn out of their advantages by <hi>Blake,</hi> and beaten with the loss of 12. Ships to their own Harbours; the <hi>Hollanders</hi> mutiny, their Fisher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are taken in whole sholes; yet in three moneths do they equip an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other great Fleet under <hi>Van Trump,</hi> who understanding our Fleet was not recruted, surprized <hi>Blake</hi> in the <hi>Downes,</hi> took and sunk 15. of his 40. Saile, and twice boarded him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, pursuing him to every Haven and sending his Ships home to teach them the new model of them: <hi>Van
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:40895:82"/> Trump</hi> himself wearing a Broom in his maintop, intimating that he would sweep the narrow Seas of all <hi>English</hi> Shipping; and his Masters setting out Edicts every day against the <hi>English</hi> trade, as the Common people did Pictures, Songs, and by-words of the late Victory.</p>
                  <p>But Blake is recruited and made 80. Saile strong, wherewith though with much loss he brushed <hi>Trump</hi> before <hi>Portland, Weymouth,</hi> and <hi>Bulloign</hi> to the loss of 11. Ships, 1500. men, whereof <hi>Blake's</hi> resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was remarkable, and <hi>Trumps</hi> conduct more; whose fortune failed in bringing his Ships on with success, but his skill did not in bringing them off with honour into <hi>Legorne,</hi> where he sunk and took most of the Ships under Captain <hi>Badily,</hi> and <hi>Appleton:</hi> their Letters mediate a peace, yet their preparations are mighty for Warr.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Trump</hi> is abroad, with 89. Ships to secure the Eastern &amp; Western Fleets; he battereth <hi>Dover,</hi> while we visit
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:40895:83"/> their Coast with an 100. Saile; at last <hi>Blake, Monke,</hi> and <hi>Dean</hi> meet and discover <hi>Trump</hi> scouring all before him; they engage, <hi>Dean</hi> is cut off in the midle by my Lord <hi>Monke,</hi> who takes no further notice of it but that the body should be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; yet <hi>Trump</hi> escapes but nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly to <hi>Dunkirke, Lawson</hi> pursu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them, <hi>Trump</hi> turnes upon him, <hi>Blake</hi> comes in, the <hi>Dutch</hi> fly, and their whole Navy is confounded; they hang a white Flagg, and send a messenger to make way for a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, their Trade is at a stand, the Souldiers mutiny for money, <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd are well paid; the Lords States come to the Ports themselves to see them set out; yet four Embassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours are sent to <hi>England,</hi> while <hi>De wit</hi> and <hi>Trump</hi> meet; my Lord <hi>Monke</hi> drawes up to them in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution with 30. Saile, and cries to 'um again; Friday they engage with equal success; Sunday (the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther clearing up) they fight again, <hi>Van Trump</hi> is killed, and the
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:40895:83"/>
                     <hi>Dutch</hi> beaten and pursued to the <hi>Texel,</hi> having but one Flagge standing. We lost 1300. men slain and wounded; they 4500. reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering but with 90. Ships of 120. into the <hi>Texel:</hi> An arbitration is set up, the right of the Flag is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, the Prince of <hi>Aurange</hi> is neglected, and a Peace conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> lasted till his Majesties return.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>L. M.</speaker>
                  <p>How did his Majesty and they part, after the entertainment 1660.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>R. B.</speaker>
                  <p>He said that he had so much kindness for them, that he would be jealous of them, if they gave a greater part of their amity to any Prince than to him, seeing he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them more than all the Princes beside, adding withall these words;</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="letter">
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Sirs, Whereas I leave here in your hands the Princess my Sister, and the Prince of</hi> Aurange, <hi>two persons who are extremely Dear to me; I pray you, Sirs, take their Interest to heart, and cause them to resent the effects of the Favour in the occasions which the Princess my
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:40895:84"/> Sister shall request of you, either for her self, or the Prince her Son, assuring you that all the Effects of your good-will shall be acknowledged of me, as if I had received them in my own Person.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>CHARLES REX.</signed>
                              </closer>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>This they recorded in the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of the States Generall, and of the Province of <hi>Holland, In Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuam rei memoriam.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:40895:84"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>